<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>digital contact tracing | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/digital-contact-tracing/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/digital-contact-tracing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>digital contact tracing</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>digital contact tracing</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/digital-contact-tracing/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>FEDORA Project Secures Funding to Explore Post-COVID Ecological Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/fedora/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/fedora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to announce that our project, “FEDORA - Federated Network Modeling of Ecological Complex Dynamical Patterns in Post-COVID,” has successfully secured funding. This pioneering initiative aims to advance the understanding of how ecological systems are affected by complex dynamical patterns emerging in the aftermath of the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FEDORA project will focus on federated network modeling to examine these complex patterns, particularly those related to wearable technology, sleep, as well as persistent symptoms observed post-COVID. Through a collaborative approach, the project will harness cutting-edge data and modeling techniques to reveal new insights into the long-term impacts of COVID-19 on ecological and human health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our interdisciplinary team will work together to develop groundbreaking models that integrate data from various sources, creating a comprehensive understanding of the interplay between ecological and health dynamics in the post-COVID world. The insights gained from this project will not only contribute to scientific knowledge but also guide future public health strategies and ecological conservation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to sharing more updates as the project progresses and invite the community to stay tuned for further developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;bmftr-logo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;FEDORA Project Logo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FEDORA Project Secures Funding to Explore Post-COVID Ecological Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/fedora/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/fedora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to announce that our project, “FEDORA - Federated Network Modeling of Ecological Complex Dynamical Patterns in Post-COVID,” has successfully secured funding. This pioneering initiative aims to advance the understanding of how ecological systems are affected by complex dynamical patterns emerging in the aftermath of the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FEDORA project will focus on federated network modeling to examine these complex patterns, particularly those related to wearable technology, sleep, as well as persistent symptoms observed post-COVID. Through a collaborative approach, the project will harness cutting-edge data and modeling techniques to reveal new insights into the long-term impacts of COVID-19 on ecological and human health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our interdisciplinary team will work together to develop groundbreaking models that integrate data from various sources, creating a comprehensive understanding of the interplay between ecological and health dynamics in the post-COVID world. The insights gained from this project will not only contribute to scientific knowledge but also guide future public health strategies and ecological conservation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to sharing more updates as the project progresses and invite the community to stay tuned for further developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;logo-federal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;FEDORA Project Logo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just published: Using smartphones to study vaccination decisions in the wild</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/smartphones_vaccination_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/smartphones_vaccination_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to share our latest research findings with the community. Recently, we have developed an innovative method in cooperation with the DTU to study how people make vaccination decisions in everyday life. For this purpose, we used a specially designed smartphone app that captures real interactions and allows us to analyze the impact of these interactions on vaccination decisions.
Our findings show that people in real decision-making situations rely more heavily on their personal experiences or personal risk assessments than on what they hear or see from others. This method allows us to better understand decision-making behavior in a real-world context.
We are confident that these new insights will provide valuable input for shaping future vaccination campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the detailed paper here:&lt;/p&gt;







  
    


&lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

   
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/publication/girardini-2024-understanding/&#34;&gt;Using smartphones to study vaccination decisions in the wild&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    
  &lt;span &gt;
  N A Girardini&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  A Stopczynski&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  O Baranov&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  C Betsch&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/authors/dirk/&#34;&gt;D Brockmann&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  S Lehmann&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  R Böhm&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span
  &gt;&lt;br /&gt;
   PLOS Digital Health 3(8): e0000550
   (2024).
  &lt;p&gt;








  

















&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pdig.0000550&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  DOI
&lt;/a&gt;



  
  
  
    
  
  
  
  
  
    
  
  &lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/digitalhealth/article?id=10.1371/journal.pdig.0000550&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
    View&lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/p&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

  


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using smartphones to study vaccination decisions in the wild</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/girardini-2024-understanding/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/girardini-2024-understanding/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out: Understanding the impact of digital contact tracing during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dct-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dct-paper/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the impact of digital contact tracing during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/burdinski-2021-tracing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/burdinski-2021-tracing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Digital contact tracing contributes little to COVID-19 outbreak containment</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/tracing_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/tracing_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our preprint &amp;ldquo;Digital contact tracing contributes little to COVID-19 outbreak containment&amp;rdquo; is out and available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As digital contact tracing apps raised the hope that they may be efficient enough to contain outbreaks
without falling back to harsher NPIs, we analyzed its success. Relying on empirical results, we find
an expected outbreak size reduction on the order of a few percent at best. While the intervention
may aid the manual tracing process, we argue that countries should concentrate on other means to contain
COVID-19 outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital contact tracing applications have been introduced in many countries to aid in the containment of
COVID-19 outbreaks. Initially, enthusiasm was high regarding their implementation as a non-pharmaceutical
intervention (NPI). Yet, no country was able to prevent larger outbreaks without falling back to harsher NPIs,
and the total effect of digital contact tracing remains elusive. Based on the results of empirical studies and
modeling efforts, we show that digital contact tracing apps might have prevented cases on the order of single-digit
percentages up until now, at best. We show that this poor impact can be attributed to a combination of low
participation rates, a non-flexible reliance on symptom-based testing, low engagement of participants, and
delays between testing and test result upload. We find that contact tracing does not change the epidemic
threshold and exclusively prevents more cases during the supercritical phase of an epidemic, making it unfit
as a tool to prevent outbreaks. Locally clustered contact structures may increase the intervention’s efficacy,
but only if the number of contacts per individual is homogeneously distributed, a condition usually not found in
contact networks.  Our results suggest that policy makers cannot rely on digital contact tracing to contain
outbreaks of COVID-19 or similar diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
