<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Preprint | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/preprint/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/preprint/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Preprint</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>Preprint</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/preprint/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint examines which simple food heuristics actually work</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/new-preprint-food/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/new-preprint-food/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New preprint examines which simple food heuristics actually work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new preprint by Kamil Fuławka, together with colleagues from the Max Planck Institute for Human Development, studies how people can make healthier food choices using simple decision rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food choices involve many nutritional dimensions at once. To reduce this complexity, people often rely on heuristics (i.e. simple decision rules) such as choosing products with less sugar or less fat. The study systematically tests a range of single-cue heuristics using large dataset of nutrient densities in food products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results show that not all heuristics perform equally well. Rules such as choose less energy, more fiber, more protein, raw foods, darker grains, and wild foods are among the most effective. Across many food comparisons, these heuristics are associated with higher levels of vitamins, minerals, protein and fiber, while often reducing salt and sugar. The heuristics focused on minimizing salt, sugar, and saturated offered no broader benefits. Thus, rather than merely warning consumers about what to avoid, the results show that signaling what foods offer—their positive nutritional attributes—can more effectively support healthier choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The preprint demonstrates how large-scale food data can be used to systematically evaluate decision heuristics in complex real world choice settings. It also provides evidence relevant for nutrition guidelines, food labeling and digital decision support tools that aim to simplify healthy eating without oversimplifying the problem itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The preprint is currently under review and can be read here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/vdaup_v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/vdaup_v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint on decision-making and large language models</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/preprint-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/preprint-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our colleague &lt;strong&gt;Kamil Fulawka&lt;/strong&gt; is the first author of a new preprint investigating how large language models (LLMs) can be used to understand the psychology of risky choice. Together with &lt;strong&gt;Ralph Hertwig&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Dirk Wulff&lt;/strong&gt;, he introduces a scalable approach to analyze participants’ free-text explanations of their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study shows that LLMs can accurately identify the reasons people give for their lottery choices in more than &lt;strong&gt;92% of cases&lt;/strong&gt;. These verbal reports reveal systematic patterns: people’s reasoning depends strongly on the &lt;strong&gt;structure of the choice problem&lt;/strong&gt; rather than being fixed across individuals. Models based on these reason profiles also achieve &lt;strong&gt;higher predictive accuracy than prospect theory&lt;/strong&gt;, one of the most established frameworks in decision science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By demonstrating the &lt;strong&gt;scientific value of verbal data&lt;/strong&gt;, the work opens new avenues for developing context-aware models of human decision-making. We are proud of Kamil’s contribution to this important line of research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/yuzmw_v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the preprint here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
