<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Phillip Lorenz-Spreen | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/phillip-lorenz-spreen/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/authors/phillip-lorenz-spreen/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Phillip Lorenz-Spreen</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>Phillip Lorenz-Spreen</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/phillip-lorenz-spreen/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Alice Weidel and the AfD benefit from Musk&#39;s attention on X?</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/x-election/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/x-election/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Has Elon Musk manipulated X to give the AfD more reach? He has made it clear in posts, articles and election events that he is a fan - and at the same time, Alice Weidel’s reach on X has increased significantly. Could these developments be linked? This blog post describes a data analysis in which we take a closer look at which accounts have received how much reach and whether Musk’s influence can be determined. Where does the sudden increase in Weidel’s reach on X come from?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: This work has not yet been peer reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, there has been a lot of fuss about Elon Musk’s possible influence in favour of the AfD. First, on 20 December, he wrote on his platform X (formerly Twitter) that only the AfD can save Germany. On 28 December, Die Welt published a guest article by Musk in which he expressed the same position. Finally, on 9 January, he held a public conversation on X with the AfD candidate Alice Weidel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As already reported in one place or another, Weidel gained a lot of reach on X. The German parliamentary administration then announced that it would investigate whether Musk is influencing the election campaign. At the same time, the EU Commission is demanding insight into possible changes to X’s recommendation algorithms. This article analyses the possible impact of Musk’s activities on the reach of the AfD and Weidel in particular on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Study Reveals Who’s Most Vulnerable to Misinformation—and why</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/misinformation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/misinformation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our junior research group leader Philipp Lorenz-Spreen, whose work focuses on the digital information environment and among other things on misinformation, has co-authored a comprehensive meta-analysis of over 256,000 decisions from thousands of participants that sheds light on who is most susceptible to misinformation and the factors behind it. Their research reveals that susceptibility depends less on formal education and more on individual and contextual factors, such as age, analytical thinking, and political alignment. Older adults and those with strong analytical skills tend to discern truth from falsehood better, though they are also more skeptical, which means they classify more news as false overall. A tendency called “true news bias” emerges when people encounter news aligning with their political beliefs or previously seen content, making them more prone to believe information without scrutiny. These findings offer valuable insights for his further studies of the spreading dynamics of misinformation and the development of interventions that help people to navigate the information environment of the internet. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2409329121&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read in full here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
