<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Adrian Zachariae | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/adrian/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/authors/adrian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Adrian Zachariae</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/authors/adrian/avatar_hufad7208688ebe21d5c4bbc29cb3c387f_782974_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpeg</url>
      <title>Adrian Zachariae</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/adrian/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Network Structure Shapes Evolutionary Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/network_structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/network_structure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our colleague &lt;strong&gt;Adrian Zachariae&lt;/strong&gt; has published a new preprint on how network structure shapes evolutionary dynamics in asexual populations. The study examines clonal interference the competition between beneficial mutations, and demonstrates that this process is strongly influenced by the topology of the underlying network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through computational modelling and a novel analytical approach inspired by epidemic research, Adrian and his co-authors show how mutation rates and network geometry interact to generate distinct evolutionary regimes. These regimes determine where high-fitness strains emerge and how they spread across the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings offer new perspectives on how spatial heterogeneity affects adaptation, with relevance for understanding pathogen evolution, conservation biology, and other complex systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.10.20.683208v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the preprint on bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origins of the Fittest: Clonal Interference in Heterogeneous Networks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/origins-of-the-fittest-2026/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/origins-of-the-fittest-2026/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clonal Interference in Heterogeneous Networks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/clonal_interference/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/clonal_interference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our research group explores the intricate relationship between complex environmental structures and evolutionary processes, focusing on clonal interference in asexual populations. We aim to understand how organisms adapt in heterogeneous, network-like environments that closely resemble real-world scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clonal interference (CI) occurs in asexual populations when multiple beneficial mutations arise and compete, unable to combine through recombination. While CI has been studied in well-mixed or simple spatial structures, its behavior in complex, heterogeneous environments remains largely unexplored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;optional_cool.gif&#34; alt=&#34;cool gif&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key Research Aims:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding CI in Highly Heterogeneous Environments: We investigate how diverse network topologies influence clonal interference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying Key Structural Components: We aim to pinpoint specific elements of network structures that significantly impact adaptive processes, understanding which features promote faster adaptation and which areas are likely sources of adaptive mutations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shaping and Controlling Adaptive Evolution: By understanding how network structures influence evolution, we seek to develop strategies for potentially guiding adaptive processes in complex environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing Analytical Tools: We&amp;rsquo;re working to create and refine mathematical and computational tools that effectively model and predict evolutionary dynamics in intricate systems, bridging network theory, evolutionary biology, and complex systems science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The insights gained from our research have potential applications across a wide range of fields. In epidemiology, our understanding of how pathogens evolve in structured host populations could form more effective disease management strategies. Conservation biologists might use our findings to guide habitat management practices, supporting species adaptation and resilience in fragmented environments. Our work could also lead to improved bioprocess designs by accounting for how environmental structure affects microbial evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond these direct applications, the principles we uncover might have broader, more speculative implications. For instance, our approaches to mutation spread in biological networks could provide insights into how content goes viral on social media platforms with diverse user structures. The competition between genetic strains in our research might elucidate how ideas, innovations and cultural practices propagate through social and professional networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we continue to explore the intricate interplay between network complexity and evolutionary dynamics, we&amp;rsquo;re not merely advancing theoretical knowledge. We&amp;rsquo;re developing a deeper, more nuanced understanding of how adaptation occurs in complex systems. This research has the potential to open new avenues for managing and harnessing evolutionary processes in various fields, spanning from biology to the social sciences. By bridging the gap between network theory and evolutionary biology, we&amp;rsquo;re paving the way for a more comprehensive understanding of how information – be it genetic, cultural, or technological – spreads and competes in our interconnected world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Import Risk</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/import_risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/import_risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our globalized world is strongly connected, on the small scale by buses, trains, cars, and on the largest, global scale by the Worldwide Air transportation Network (WAN).
It is likely that our connectivity has not reached its peak yet, since for example the number of globally scheduled air passengers increased yearly by about 6% between 2004 and 2019.
The connectivity has immense consequences on the propagation of disease since alongside passengers everything that sticks to them, such as bacteria, viruses, earth clumps beneath their shoes etc. comes with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project crosses the fields of network science, transportation, mobility and disease dynamics and it&amp;rsquo;s an offspring of the idea to not use the conventional distance (in meter, miles, feet &amp;hellip; pick your unit) as a metric but an &lt;strong&gt;effective distance&lt;/strong&gt; that is based on the mobility between regions.
When - $P(B | A)$ is the probability to travel to B from A (which is computed from mobility fluxes) than the effective distance is $ d _{\text{eff}} (A | B) = d_0 - log (P(i| n_0)) $ -.
In the seminal paper by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.1245200&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Brockmann and Helbing (2013)&lt;/a&gt; _effective distance $d _{\text{eff}}$ - was shown to linearly correlate with the arrival time of diseases as shown in Fig. 2.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/eff_dist_paper_adapted_1.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;Full&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 2 - The shortest path tree based on the &lt;b&gt;effective distance&lt;/b&gt; with the airport of Hong Kong as origin (&lt;b&gt;A&lt;/b&gt;) and how a pandemic spreads around the globe (&lt;b&gt;B&lt;/b&gt;).
  While the spread on the world map seems rather random, you see a nice circular wave spreading in the effective distance tree, illustrating the linear correlation to disease arrival times.
  Adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.1245200&#34;&gt;Brockmann and Helbing&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our recent paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011775&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Klamser et al. (2024),&lt;/a&gt; we deepen the connection between the effective distance shortest path tree, spreading dynamics and mobility.
We present a way to estimate the passenger flow between any two airports (including those without direct connections) given that we only know the number and maximal capacity of planes (see illustrative example in Fig. 3).
In the end, the method allows us to estimate the number of infected passenger leaving B when we know the number of infected that entered A.
Thus, we know the risk of importation and why it is named &lt;b&gt;import risk method&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/relrisk.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;400&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 3 - Import Risk Example: 100 infected passengers board planes at airport X en route to destination airports elsewhere in the network, going through transit airports in the process. The relative import risk at a given destination is the fraction of the 100 individuals that entered at airport X and exited at that destination airport (red).
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mechanistic idea behind the import risk method is to let a random walker start at node B of the WAN and exit at each node with a probability derived from the effective distance shortest path tree.
The final fraction of times it leaves at node A is the import risk probability.
Now, this method is parameter free and motivated by disease dynamics, but at the same time it provides a method to estimate mobility on a global scale.
The mobility estimation is a classic task in transportation science with well-established models as the gravity model (proposed in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2087063?casa_token=5goDmVg4aOkAAAAA%3A6Y9zup7UcSjT8DQ1izhRza_-N568nGLP_43ikQys0Vzoux-4qaYKp1u0Cruz2YwZ2hggPU2PIKW4oqbB6xnFtaJIgj-oX_zCbMwLneoPv8OzCdsFXA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;1946 by Zipf&lt;/a&gt;).
A core aspect of our import risk paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011775&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Klamser et al. (2024)&lt;/a&gt; is to compare our method to established mobility models.
We found that our approach outperforms the established models, and the crazy thing is, that our method is parameter free, while the gravity model always needs parameter estimation (one needs to know the real mobility flow beforehand).
This holds true if we check the prediction quality for the 10 countries with the highest import probability, which is especially important for disease propagation since these countries are the one that should increase their passenger control (shown in Fig. 4).&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/ir_paper_fig_10cntrs.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;800&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 4 - Mobility model comparisons for top 10 import countries: The well-established gravity model with exponential (&lt;b&gt;A&lt;/b&gt;) and power-law (&lt;b&gt;B&lt;/b&gt;) distance decay, the parameter free radiation model (&lt;b&gt;C&lt;/b&gt;) and our import risk model (&lt;b&gt;D&lt;/b&gt;).
  Each dot is a country that is among the 10 countries with the highest import probability from another country (10 target countries x 183 source countries).
  A true or false positive (T.Pos. or F. Pos.) means that the country is or is not among the 10 countries with the highest reference import probability.
  A false negative (F. Neg.) means that it belongs according to reference it is among the top 10 but was not detected by the respective model.
  Figure adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011775&#34;&gt;Klamser et al. (2024)&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We applied the measure during COVID-19 to estimate the countries that have been reached by Omicron without it being detected &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/reports/importrisk_omicron_update/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
And in a big cooperation with great colleagues that have been put together by &lt;a href=&#34;https://manliodedomenico.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Manlio De Domenico,&lt;/a&gt; we have developed and validated a framework (&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/pnasnexus/article/2/6/pgad192/7191545?login=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Klamser and d&amp;rsquo;Andrea et al. (2023)&lt;/a&gt;)that can estimate from sparse and noisy samples via phylogenetic analysis the time when the variant first occurred in the country of origin, how it spreads across the globe with our import risk model, and how the countries are affected by a disease dynamic model.
We were even able to smash everything into one number, which we call the &lt;strong&gt;pandemic delay&lt;/strong&gt;, that estimates how long it takes for a new emerging variant to make out 10% of all current cases in a respective country.
It revealed that only by combining mobility data with a phylogenetic estimate of the reproduction number, the pandemic potentials of the lineages are correctly
assessed relative to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing global preparedness during an ongoing pandemic from partial and noisy data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2023-enhancing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2023-enhancing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Enhancing global preparedness during an ongoing pandemic from partial and noisy data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Monitor: Contact patterns during the Pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/contact_monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/contact_monitor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to mobility, we now show the average contacts in the population over time—with equally important insights into the course of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mobility of people gives us an important overview of the pandemic, but it is actually the contacts between people that are instrumental in the infection dynamics: Transmissions occur when people meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the new &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/contact-index/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;contact monitor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we make these contacts visible. The monitor shows the average number of contacts that a person in Germany had on a given day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can clearly see how strongly contacts have decreased in March 2020, and how they are still at a low level more than a year after the start of the pandemic. Also visible are the different phases of the pandemic and reactions to it with lockdowns, relaxations, holidays and vacations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of contacts is calculated from GPS mobile phone data and provided to us as an anonymous, aggregated statistic - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/data-info/contacts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;more on the methodology here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will continue to analyze contact dynamics and investigate what conclusions can be drawn about infection dynamics. For example, in the study &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/118/31/e2026731118&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ruediger et al.&lt;/a&gt;, contacts were shown to be related to the reproductive number R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact Index Monitor</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/contactindex-monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/contactindex-monitor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;contact-index-monitor&#34;&gt;Contact Index Monitor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;width: 100%; height: 450px; border: 1px solid #ddd; margin: 20px 0;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe 
    src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/viz/contactindex-monitor/&#34; 
    width=&#34;100%&#34; 
    height=&#34;100%&#34; 
    frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
    style=&#34;border: none;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How a pandemic develops depends on many factors: the biology of the pathogen, its susceptibility to external influences such as humidity and temperature, but most of all it is determined by contacts between individuals: transmissions occur primarily when people have contact with each other. The number of contacts thus gives us an insight into the course of the pandemic. Fewer contacts make it more difficult for the pathogen to spread through the population, whereas more contacts promote rapid spread. In the Contacts Monitor, we show the number of contacts and its variation in Germany over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;width: 100%; height: 1000px; border: 1px solid #ddd; margin: 20px 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe 
    src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/viz/contactindex-monitor/states.html&#34; 
    width=&#34;100%&#34; 
    height=&#34;100%&#34; 
    frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
    scrolling=&#34;no&#34;
    style=&#34;border: none; overflow: hidden;
    onload=&#34;this.contentDocument.body.style.overflow=&#39;hidden&#39;;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new COVID-19 mobility monitor report ist online</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/mobility_between_counties/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/mobility_between_counties/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You can find the whole report here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/reports/traffic-grid/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;** -&amp;gt; Traffic Between Adjacent Counties &amp;lt;- **&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/reports/adjacent-travel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;found on the covid-19-mobility monitor site&lt;/a&gt; but is also available as an &lt;a href=&#34;https://observablehq.com/@adrianzachariae/traffic-lattice-germany&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Observable notebook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just published: Social networks predict the life and death of honey bees</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/bee_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/bee_paper/</guid>
      <description>






  
    


&lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

   
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/publication/wild-2020-social/&#34;&gt;Social networks predict the life and death of honey bees&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    
  &lt;span &gt;
  B Wild&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  D M Dormagen&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/authors/adrian/&#34;&gt;A Zachariae&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  M L Smith&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  K S Traynor&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/authors/dirk/&#34;&gt;D Brockmann&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  I D Couzin&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  T Landgraf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span
  &gt;&lt;br /&gt;
   Nature Communications 12, 1110
   (2021).
  &lt;p&gt;








  
    
  



&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-21212-5.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  PDF
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm js-cite-modal&#34;
        data-filename=&#34;/publication/wild-2020-social/cite.bib&#34;&gt;
  Cite
&lt;/a&gt;













&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21212-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  DOI
&lt;/a&gt;



  
  
  
    
  
  
  
  
  
    
  
  &lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-21212-5#citeas&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
    View&lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/p&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

  


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social networks predict the life and death of honey bees</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/wild-2020-social/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/wild-2020-social/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new COVID-19 mobility monitor report ist online</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/new_mobility_report/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/new_mobility_report/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You can find the whole report here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/reports/adjacent-travel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;** -&amp;gt; Traffic in the Pandemic by Distance &amp;lt;- **&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In past reports we have shown repeatedly that the change in mobility during the pandemic affects local and long-distance traffic differently. Recently, there has been increased interest in traffic-by-distance, as actual and proposed policies like the “15-km rule” have targeted long-distance travel to limit the spread from COVID-19 hotspots to neighboring areas and beyond. This report explores &lt;strong&gt;how much traffic remains local&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;how much crosses borders&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;how drastic regional differences are&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/reports/adjacent-travel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;found on the covid-19-mobility monitor site&lt;/a&gt; but is also available as an &lt;a href=&#34;https://observablehq.com/@adrianzachariae/traffic-in-the-pandemic-by-distance&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Observable notebook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Corona Datenspende App</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/datenspende/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/datenspende/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 lockdown induces disease-mitigating structural changes in mobility networks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2020-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2020-covid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
