<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>digital epidemiology | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/digital-epidemiology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/digital-epidemiology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>digital epidemiology</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>digital epidemiology</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/digital-epidemiology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 Detection from Wearables</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/covid_detection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/covid_detection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Controlling the spread of infectious diseases early in a pandemic is crucial. The recent COVID-19 outbreak and its rapid global spread highlight the urgent need for tools that can limit the spreading of infectious diseases at the earliest stage possible to prevent global pandemics.
Previous research has suggested the potential to detect COVID-19 infections through the observation of physiological alterations occurring after the onset of the disease, including elevated resting heart rates, extended sleep durations, and decreased physical activity. Wearable sensors, equipped to monitor these changes, in conjunction with machine learning algorithms trained on data from these sensors, could identify these variations, thus providing a method to quickly classify individuals as infected.
Utilizing wearable sensor data from the Corona Data Donation Project, which encompasses resting heart rate, step count, and sleep duration time series from over 120,000 voluntary participants, a Logistic Regression model was developed for the classification of submitted COVID-19 test results. This model achieved classification success, as evidenced by a Receiver Operating Characteristic Area Under the Curve (ROC AUC) of 0.58, precision of 0.26, and recall of 0.54. The implementation of the catch22 feature set for feature extraction from the submitted wearable sensor data enhanced the interpretability of the classification algorithm. It also enables a more detailed analysis of the specific physiological changes used to differentiate individuals testing positive or negative for COVID-19.
This study emphasizes the capability of predicting COVID-19 across large cohorts and underscores the value of employing infectious disease prediction models based on wearable sensor data as an additional public health tool.
&lt;strong&gt;The LR model presented in Fig. 1 demonstrated&lt;/strong&gt; prediction capabilities for COVID-19 test results surpassing random chance, thereby facilitating the early detection of this infectious disease. Additionally, the incorporation of catch22 features into the feature engineering process enhanced the interpretability of the classification decisions made by the model.
The predictive LR model shown in Fig. 1 demonstrated satisfactory performance, notable given the voluntary nature of data submission, the impossibility of verifying correct and constant wear of devices, reliance on daily averages, absence of precise test and symptom onset dates, and the utilization of multiple devices across a broad cohort. The present study introduced a predictive model that has been trained on a considerable cohort size, addressing concerns from existing research about models only trained on significantly smaller cohorts. Additionally, this study tackled the issue of geographic underrepresentation by developing a predictive model for COVID-19 classification with data donated outside the United States, addressing other concerns in existing literature.
Additionally confirmatory models have been developed which showed performances consistent with existing literature, validating its efficacy in confirming COVID-19 infections within this study’s framework. Enhancements in confirmatory capability were noted with the increasing days included after a COVID-19 test submission, indicating that a longer observational period bolsters the model’s confirmatory power. Employing interpretable catch22 feature engineering provided clarity in the classification process and verified that the detected signals coincide with physiological responses to COVID-19 infection, as shown in Fig. 2 and 3. This consistency in signal detection across the models and their alignment with other research accentuates the catch22 features’ ability to accurately capture vital data signals from wearable sensor data. Conclusively, this study proposes a combined approach of catch22 feature engineering and machine learning classification algorithms as an effective strategy in combating the rapid spread of infectious diseases. Highlighting that this methodology could be particulary valuable in the initial stages of a pandemic, where traditional methods might be unavailable. Thus, it offers an essential addition to public health resources. This study stresses the potential of utilizing wearable sensor data, combined with automated feature engineering and machine learning classification algorithms, for the detection and confirmation of diseases like COVID-19. With additional advancements machine learning approaches to detect illnesses like COVID-19 using wearable sensor data could significantly improve the readiness and response to future public health crise&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/paul_w2.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;Full&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 2 - Permutation Feature Importance for the test dataset for the Confirmatory LR: Focusing on features that led to a mean increase in model performance (increase in Geometric Mean (GM)). This represents a selection from the complete set of features. Each box displayed on the dashed line in the plot illustrates the range from the first to the third quartile of the GM reduction observed over 100 iterations for each catch22 feature. The median reduction in GM is denoted by the orange line within each box. The whiskers extend to the most extreme GM reduction value that falls within 1.5 times the interquartile range from the edges of the box. Any outliers are represented by dots.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/paul_w3.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;Full&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 3 - Permutation Feature Importance for the test dataset for the Confirmatory XGBoost Model: Focusing on features that led to a mean increase in model performance (increase in Geometric Mean (GM)). This represents a selection from the complete set of features. Each box displayed on the dashed line in the plot illustrates the range from the first to the third quartile of the GM reduction observed over 100 iterations for each catch22 feature. The median reduction in GM is denoted by the orange line within each box. The whiskers extend to the most extreme GM reduction value that falls within 1.5 times the interquartile range from the edges of the box. Any outliers are represented by dots.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FEDORA Project Secures Funding to Explore Post-COVID Ecological Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/fedora/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/fedora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to announce that our project, “FEDORA - Federated Network Modeling of Ecological Complex Dynamical Patterns in Post-COVID,” has successfully secured funding. This pioneering initiative aims to advance the understanding of how ecological systems are affected by complex dynamical patterns emerging in the aftermath of the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FEDORA project will focus on federated network modeling to examine these complex patterns, particularly those related to wearable technology, sleep, as well as persistent symptoms observed post-COVID. Through a collaborative approach, the project will harness cutting-edge data and modeling techniques to reveal new insights into the long-term impacts of COVID-19 on ecological and human health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our interdisciplinary team will work together to develop groundbreaking models that integrate data from various sources, creating a comprehensive understanding of the interplay between ecological and health dynamics in the post-COVID world. The insights gained from this project will not only contribute to scientific knowledge but also guide future public health strategies and ecological conservation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to sharing more updates as the project progresses and invite the community to stay tuned for further developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;bmftr-logo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;FEDORA Project Logo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FEDORA Project Secures Funding to Explore Post-COVID Ecological Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/fedora/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/fedora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to announce that our project, “FEDORA - Federated Network Modeling of Ecological Complex Dynamical Patterns in Post-COVID,” has successfully secured funding. This pioneering initiative aims to advance the understanding of how ecological systems are affected by complex dynamical patterns emerging in the aftermath of the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FEDORA project will focus on federated network modeling to examine these complex patterns, particularly those related to wearable technology, sleep, as well as persistent symptoms observed post-COVID. Through a collaborative approach, the project will harness cutting-edge data and modeling techniques to reveal new insights into the long-term impacts of COVID-19 on ecological and human health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our interdisciplinary team will work together to develop groundbreaking models that integrate data from various sources, creating a comprehensive understanding of the interplay between ecological and health dynamics in the post-COVID world. The insights gained from this project will not only contribute to scientific knowledge but also guide future public health strategies and ecological conservation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to sharing more updates as the project progresses and invite the community to stay tuned for further developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;logo-federal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;FEDORA Project Logo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Import Risk</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/import_risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/import_risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our globalized world is strongly connected, on the small scale by buses, trains, cars, and on the largest, global scale by the Worldwide Air transportation Network (WAN).
It is likely that our connectivity has not reached its peak yet, since for example the number of globally scheduled air passengers increased yearly by about 6% between 2004 and 2019.
The connectivity has immense consequences on the propagation of disease since alongside passengers everything that sticks to them, such as bacteria, viruses, earth clumps beneath their shoes etc. comes with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project crosses the fields of network science, transportation, mobility and disease dynamics and it&amp;rsquo;s an offspring of the idea to not use the conventional distance (in meter, miles, feet &amp;hellip; pick your unit) as a metric but an &lt;strong&gt;effective distance&lt;/strong&gt; that is based on the mobility between regions.
When - $P(B | A)$ is the probability to travel to B from A (which is computed from mobility fluxes) than the effective distance is $ d _{\text{eff}} (A | B) = d_0 - log (P(i| n_0)) $ -.
In the seminal paper by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.1245200&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Brockmann and Helbing (2013)&lt;/a&gt; _effective distance $d _{\text{eff}}$ - was shown to linearly correlate with the arrival time of diseases as shown in Fig. 2.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/eff_dist_paper_adapted_1.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;Full&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 2 - The shortest path tree based on the &lt;b&gt;effective distance&lt;/b&gt; with the airport of Hong Kong as origin (&lt;b&gt;A&lt;/b&gt;) and how a pandemic spreads around the globe (&lt;b&gt;B&lt;/b&gt;).
  While the spread on the world map seems rather random, you see a nice circular wave spreading in the effective distance tree, illustrating the linear correlation to disease arrival times.
  Adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.1245200&#34;&gt;Brockmann and Helbing&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our recent paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011775&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Klamser et al. (2024),&lt;/a&gt; we deepen the connection between the effective distance shortest path tree, spreading dynamics and mobility.
We present a way to estimate the passenger flow between any two airports (including those without direct connections) given that we only know the number and maximal capacity of planes (see illustrative example in Fig. 3).
In the end, the method allows us to estimate the number of infected passenger leaving B when we know the number of infected that entered A.
Thus, we know the risk of importation and why it is named &lt;b&gt;import risk method&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/relrisk.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;400&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 3 - Import Risk Example: 100 infected passengers board planes at airport X en route to destination airports elsewhere in the network, going through transit airports in the process. The relative import risk at a given destination is the fraction of the 100 individuals that entered at airport X and exited at that destination airport (red).
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mechanistic idea behind the import risk method is to let a random walker start at node B of the WAN and exit at each node with a probability derived from the effective distance shortest path tree.
The final fraction of times it leaves at node A is the import risk probability.
Now, this method is parameter free and motivated by disease dynamics, but at the same time it provides a method to estimate mobility on a global scale.
The mobility estimation is a classic task in transportation science with well-established models as the gravity model (proposed in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2087063?casa_token=5goDmVg4aOkAAAAA%3A6Y9zup7UcSjT8DQ1izhRza_-N568nGLP_43ikQys0Vzoux-4qaYKp1u0Cruz2YwZ2hggPU2PIKW4oqbB6xnFtaJIgj-oX_zCbMwLneoPv8OzCdsFXA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;1946 by Zipf&lt;/a&gt;).
A core aspect of our import risk paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011775&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Klamser et al. (2024)&lt;/a&gt; is to compare our method to established mobility models.
We found that our approach outperforms the established models, and the crazy thing is, that our method is parameter free, while the gravity model always needs parameter estimation (one needs to know the real mobility flow beforehand).
This holds true if we check the prediction quality for the 10 countries with the highest import probability, which is especially important for disease propagation since these countries are the one that should increase their passenger control (shown in Fig. 4).&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/ir_paper_fig_10cntrs.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;800&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 4 - Mobility model comparisons for top 10 import countries: The well-established gravity model with exponential (&lt;b&gt;A&lt;/b&gt;) and power-law (&lt;b&gt;B&lt;/b&gt;) distance decay, the parameter free radiation model (&lt;b&gt;C&lt;/b&gt;) and our import risk model (&lt;b&gt;D&lt;/b&gt;).
  Each dot is a country that is among the 10 countries with the highest import probability from another country (10 target countries x 183 source countries).
  A true or false positive (T.Pos. or F. Pos.) means that the country is or is not among the 10 countries with the highest reference import probability.
  A false negative (F. Neg.) means that it belongs according to reference it is among the top 10 but was not detected by the respective model.
  Figure adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011775&#34;&gt;Klamser et al. (2024)&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We applied the measure during COVID-19 to estimate the countries that have been reached by Omicron without it being detected &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/reports/importrisk_omicron_update/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
And in a big cooperation with great colleagues that have been put together by &lt;a href=&#34;https://manliodedomenico.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Manlio De Domenico,&lt;/a&gt; we have developed and validated a framework (&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/pnasnexus/article/2/6/pgad192/7191545?login=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Klamser and d&amp;rsquo;Andrea et al. (2023)&lt;/a&gt;)that can estimate from sparse and noisy samples via phylogenetic analysis the time when the variant first occurred in the country of origin, how it spreads across the globe with our import risk model, and how the countries are affected by a disease dynamic model.
We were even able to smash everything into one number, which we call the &lt;strong&gt;pandemic delay&lt;/strong&gt;, that estimates how long it takes for a new emerging variant to make out 10% of all current cases in a respective country.
It revealed that only by combining mobility data with a phylogenetic estimate of the reproduction number, the pandemic potentials of the lineages are correctly
assessed relative to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just published: Using smartphones to study vaccination decisions in the wild</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/smartphones_vaccination_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/smartphones_vaccination_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to share our latest research findings with the community. Recently, we have developed an innovative method in cooperation with the DTU to study how people make vaccination decisions in everyday life. For this purpose, we used a specially designed smartphone app that captures real interactions and allows us to analyze the impact of these interactions on vaccination decisions.
Our findings show that people in real decision-making situations rely more heavily on their personal experiences or personal risk assessments than on what they hear or see from others. This method allows us to better understand decision-making behavior in a real-world context.
We are confident that these new insights will provide valuable input for shaping future vaccination campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the detailed paper here:&lt;/p&gt;







  
    


&lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

   
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/publication/girardini-2024-understanding/&#34;&gt;Using smartphones to study vaccination decisions in the wild&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    
  &lt;span &gt;
  N A Girardini&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  A Stopczynski&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  O Baranov&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  C Betsch&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/authors/dirk/&#34;&gt;D Brockmann&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  S Lehmann&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  R Böhm&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span
  &gt;&lt;br /&gt;
   PLOS Digital Health 3(8): e0000550
   (2024).
  &lt;p&gt;








  

















&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pdig.0000550&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  DOI
&lt;/a&gt;



  
  
  
    
  
  
  
  
  
    
  
  &lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/digitalhealth/article?id=10.1371/journal.pdig.0000550&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
    View&lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/p&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

  


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using smartphones to study vaccination decisions in the wild</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/girardini-2024-understanding/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/girardini-2024-understanding/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint: Estimating the distribution of COVID-19-susceptible, -recovered, and -vaccinated individuals in Germany up to April 2022</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/sero_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/sero_preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.04.19.22274030v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.04.19.22274030v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint: Evidence for positive long- and short-term effects of vaccinations against COVID-19 in wearable sensor metrics -- Insights from the German Corona Data Donation Project</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/long_covid_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/long_covid_preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we use physiological data collected in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.de/science/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;German Data Donation Project (Datenspende)&lt;/a&gt; to investigate the differential impact of vaccination on the effect that a COVID-19 infection has on &lt;strong&gt;resting heart rate&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;physical activity&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sleep&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02846&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02846&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digitale Epidemiologie</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/brockmann-2020-digitale/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/brockmann-2020-digitale/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
