<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>modelling | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/modelling/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/modelling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>modelling</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>modelling</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/modelling/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fungal Growth</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/fungal_growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/fungal_growth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Fungi interact in a mycorrhizal symbiosis with plants or are simple decomposers of organic matter.
In this project, we investigate the growth of filamentous fungi by creating and investigating mathematical growth models.
We cooperate with experimental biologists from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aguilar-ecology.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;aguilar ecology lab&lt;/a&gt; who have a profound knowledge of the growth patterns of different fungal species (see Fig.1).
In a first &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/ismecommun/article/2/1/2/7460968&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;network analysis of our collaborators&lt;/a&gt;, they identified that some network traits vary most in between species, as for example the meshedness (how different the network is from a fully-connected one without crossing edges).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/2022Aguilar_network_paper_fig3adapted.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;800&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Fig.1 - Different species of hyphal growing fungi and the reconstruction of the network they are forming.
  Figure is adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/ismecommun/article/2/1/2/7460968&#34;&gt;Aguilar-Trigueros et al. (2022)&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We address the problem from a modeling perspective, that means we build an agent-based model, which is motivated from real fungi.
In our model each agent represents the tip of a hyphen and the tip as well as the whole hyphen release an enzyme.
This enzyme diffuses though the environment and other tips/agents can sense the local concentration and gradient.
This is all the information the tip has about its environment, i.e. only local information is allowed.
New Tips/Agents are created either by an apical branching event, at which one tip splits in two, or by a lateral branching event, where from the lower half of a tip compartment multiple branches grow perpendicular to the local growth direction.
By varying some fundamental parameters of the model as the diffusion coefficient, the enzyme release rate or the number of lateral branches, different shapes can emerge as shown if Fig. 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/3_mycel_compilation.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;1200&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Fig.2 -
  Depending on the parameters, the mycelium grows densely (A) or less densely (B, C) if for example the enzyme release rate is increased (B)  or the septation rule is adapted (C). The enzyme in the environment (orange and red background color) inhibits the growth of the mycelium, thus the mycelium is more responsive to its own form (compare A with B). In (A, B) the septation and lateral branching form always two septa and branches at each septation event. In (C) 6 septa and branches are formed during a septation event. While the quadrants 2-4 show the concentration on a variable linear scale (bottom color bar), the 1st quadrant uses a fixed logarithmic scale (top color bar) to enable a fair comparison between simulations.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goals are now to reproduce key structural properties of real fungal species with a model as simple as possible, study the statistical properties of the different phases of the model and what task the fungi can perform beast at every phase.
This is exciting, especially because we are able to switch between theory, modelling and experiments.
The big picture is of course the role of the fungi in the ecosystems in connection with their growth strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for positive long- and short-term effects of vaccinations against COVID-19 in wearable sensor metrics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/wiedermann-2023-evidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/wiedermann-2023-evidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing global preparedness during an ongoing pandemic from partial and noisy data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2023-enhancing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2023-enhancing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the impact of the Omicron infection wave in Germany</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-modeling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the share of SARS-CoV-2- immunologically naïve individuals in Germany up to June 2022</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-estimating/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-estimating/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing and predicting the spatial evolution of Carbapenemase-producing Enterobacteriaceae outbreaks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/myall-2023-reconstructing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/myall-2023-reconstructing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out: Understanding the impact of digital contact tracing during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dct-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dct-paper/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the impact of digital contact tracing during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/burdinski-2021-tracing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/burdinski-2021-tracing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Enhancing global preparedness during an ongoing pandemic from partial and noisy data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Preprint Out: Modeling the impact of the Omicron infection wave in Germany</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2021, the first case of SARS-CoV-2 “variant of concern” (VOC) B.1.1.529 (“Omicron”) was reported in Germany, alongside global reports of reduced vaccine efficacy against infections with this variant. The potential threat posed by the rapid spread of this variant in Germany remained, at the time, elusive.
We developed a variant-dependent population-averaged susceptible-exposed-infected-recovered (SEIR) infectious disease model. The model was calibrated on the observed fixation dynamics of the Omicron variant in December 2021, and allowed us to estimate potential courses of upcoming infection waves in Germany, focusing on the corresponding burden on intensive care units (ICUs) and the efficacy of contact reduction strategies. A maximum median incidence of approximately 300 000 (50% PI in 1000: [181,454], 95% PI in 1000: [55,804]) reported cases per day was expected with the median peak occurring in the mid of February 2022, reaching a cumulative Omicron case count of 16.5 million (50% PI in mio: [11.4, 21.3], 95% PI in mio: [4.1, 27.9]) until Apr 1, 2022. These figures were in line with the actual Omicron waves that were subsequently observed in Germany with respective peaks occurring in mid February (peak: 191k daily new cases) and mid March (peak: 230k daily new cases), cumulatively infecting 14.8 million individuals during the study period. The model peak incidence was observed to be highly sensitive to variations in the assumed generation time and decreased with shorter generation time. Low contact reductions were expected to lead to containment. Early, strict, and short contact reductions could have led to a strong “rebound” effect with high incidences after the end of the respective non-pharmaceutical interventions. Higher vaccine uptake would have led to a lower outbreak size. To ensure that ICU occupancy remained below maximum capacity, a relative risk of requiring ICU care of 10%–20% was necessary (after infection with Omicron vs. infection with Delta).
We expected a large cumulative number of infections with the VOC Omicron in Germany with ICU occupancy likely remaining below capacity nevertheless, even without additional non-pharmaceutical interventions. Our estimates were in line with the retrospectively observed waves. The results presented here informed legislation in Germany. The methodology developed in this study might be used to estimate the impact of future waves of COVID-19 or other infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abschätzung der Infektionswelle durch die SARS-CoV-2 VOC Omikron</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-omicron/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-omicron/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Digital contact tracing contributes little to COVID-19 outbreak containment</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/tracing_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/tracing_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our preprint &amp;ldquo;Digital contact tracing contributes little to COVID-19 outbreak containment&amp;rdquo; is out and available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As digital contact tracing apps raised the hope that they may be efficient enough to contain outbreaks
without falling back to harsher NPIs, we analyzed its success. Relying on empirical results, we find
an expected outbreak size reduction on the order of a few percent at best. While the intervention
may aid the manual tracing process, we argue that countries should concentrate on other means to contain
COVID-19 outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital contact tracing applications have been introduced in many countries to aid in the containment of
COVID-19 outbreaks. Initially, enthusiasm was high regarding their implementation as a non-pharmaceutical
intervention (NPI). Yet, no country was able to prevent larger outbreaks without falling back to harsher NPIs,
and the total effect of digital contact tracing remains elusive. Based on the results of empirical studies and
modeling efforts, we show that digital contact tracing apps might have prevented cases on the order of single-digit
percentages up until now, at best. We show that this poor impact can be attributed to a combination of low
participation rates, a non-flexible reliance on symptom-based testing, low engagement of participants, and
delays between testing and test result upload. We find that contact tracing does not change the epidemic
threshold and exclusively prevents more cases during the supercritical phase of an epidemic, making it unfit
as a tool to prevent outbreaks. Locally clustered contact structures may increase the intervention’s efficacy,
but only if the number of contacts per individual is homogeneously distributed, a condition usually not found in
contact networks.  Our results suggest that policy makers cannot rely on digital contact tracing to contain
outbreaks of COVID-19 or similar diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are happy that our preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2102.13600.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is out and available on &lt;em&gt;arxiv.org&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a very constructive and effective collaborative effort, lead by our &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/author/dr.-benjamin-f.-maier/&#34;&gt;Ben Maier&lt;/a&gt;, who did all the heavy lifting, and valuable contributions by the teams of Cornelia Betsch, Michael Meyer-Hermann and by Karl Lauterbach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell we evaluate and compare different vaccination strageties of COVID-19 mRNA-vaccines in high-risk groups in Germany and show that a flexible scheduling of the second vaccine dose can potentially be the way to go. If you are interested in the details, have a look at the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vaccination against COVID-19 with the recently approved mRNA vaccines BNT162b2 (BioNTech/Pfizer) and mRNA-1273 (Moderna) is currently underway in a large number of countries. However, high incidence rates and rapidly spreading SARS-CoV-2 variants are concerning. In combination with acute supply deficits in Europe in early 2021, the question arises of whether stretching the vaccine, for instance by delaying the second dose, can make a significant contribution to preventing deaths, despite associated risks such as lower vaccine efficacy, the potential emergence of escape mutants, enhancement, waning immunity, reduced social acceptance of off-label vaccination, and liability shifts. A quantitative epidemiological assessment of risks and benefits of non-standard vaccination protocols remains elusive. To clarify the situation and to provide a quantitative epidemiological foundation we develop a stochastic epidemiological model that integrates specific vaccine rollout protocols into a risk-group structured infectious disease dynamical model. Using the situation and conditions in Germany as a reference system, we show that delaying the second vaccine dose is expected to prevent deaths in the four to five digit range, should the incidence resurge. We show that this considerable public health benefit relies on the fact that both mRNA vaccines provide substantial protection against severe COVID-19 and death beginning 12 to 14 days after the first dose. The benefits of protocol change are attenuated should vaccine compliance decrease substantially. To quantify the impact of protocol change on vaccination adherence we performed a large-scale online survey. We find that, in Germany, changing vaccination protocols may lead to small reductions in vaccination intention. In sum, we therefore expect the benefits of a strategy change to remain substantial and stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
