<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Frank Schlosser | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/frank/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/authors/frank/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Frank Schlosser</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/authors/frank/avatar_hu1155224a6332ce5f240acf42565e2e39_201251_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Frank Schlosser</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/frank/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the impact of the Omicron infection wave in Germany</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-modeling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Preprint Out: Modeling the impact of the Omicron infection wave in Germany</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2021, the first case of SARS-CoV-2 “variant of concern” (VOC) B.1.1.529 (“Omicron”) was reported in Germany, alongside global reports of reduced vaccine efficacy against infections with this variant. The potential threat posed by the rapid spread of this variant in Germany remained, at the time, elusive.
We developed a variant-dependent population-averaged susceptible-exposed-infected-recovered (SEIR) infectious disease model. The model was calibrated on the observed fixation dynamics of the Omicron variant in December 2021, and allowed us to estimate potential courses of upcoming infection waves in Germany, focusing on the corresponding burden on intensive care units (ICUs) and the efficacy of contact reduction strategies. A maximum median incidence of approximately 300 000 (50% PI in 1000: [181,454], 95% PI in 1000: [55,804]) reported cases per day was expected with the median peak occurring in the mid of February 2022, reaching a cumulative Omicron case count of 16.5 million (50% PI in mio: [11.4, 21.3], 95% PI in mio: [4.1, 27.9]) until Apr 1, 2022. These figures were in line with the actual Omicron waves that were subsequently observed in Germany with respective peaks occurring in mid February (peak: 191k daily new cases) and mid March (peak: 230k daily new cases), cumulatively infecting 14.8 million individuals during the study period. The model peak incidence was observed to be highly sensitive to variations in the assumed generation time and decreased with shorter generation time. Low contact reductions were expected to lead to containment. Early, strict, and short contact reductions could have led to a strong “rebound” effect with high incidences after the end of the respective non-pharmaceutical interventions. Higher vaccine uptake would have led to a lower outbreak size. To ensure that ICU occupancy remained below maximum capacity, a relative risk of requiring ICU care of 10%–20% was necessary (after infection with Omicron vs. infection with Delta).
We expected a large cumulative number of infections with the VOC Omicron in Germany with ICU occupancy likely remaining below capacity nevertheless, even without additional non-pharmaceutical interventions. Our estimates were in line with the retrospectively observed waves. The results presented here informed legislation in Germany. The methodology developed in this study might be used to estimate the impact of future waves of COVID-19 or other infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abschätzung der Infektionswelle durch die SARS-CoV-2 VOC Omikron</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-omicron/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-omicron/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biases in human mobility data impact epidemic modeling</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2021-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2021-bias/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding disease outbreak locations from human mobility data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2021-finding/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2021-finding/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out: Finding disease outbreak locations from human mobility data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/outbreak_detection/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/outbreak_detection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we investigated how much information on individual mobility patterns is required
to reconstruct the origin of an outbreak from spatially distributed cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out: not so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://epjdatascience.springeropen.com/articles/10.1140/epjds/s13688-021-00306-6#citeas&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding the origin location of an infectious disease outbreak quickly is crucial in
mitigating its further dissemination. Current methods to identify outbreak locations
early on rely on interviewing affected individuals and correlating their movements,
which is a manual, time-consuming, and error-prone process. Other methods such as
contact tracing, genomic sequencing or theoretical models of epidemic spread offer
help, but they are not applicable at the onset of an outbreak as they require highly
processed information or established transmission chains. Digital data sources such as
mobile phones offer new ways to find outbreak sources in an automated way. Here,
we propose a novel method to determine outbreak origins from geolocated
movement data of individuals affected by the outbreak. Our algorithm scans
movement trajectories for shared locations and identifies the outbreak origin as the
most dominant among them. We test the method using various empirical and
synthetic datasets, and demonstrate that it is able to single out the true outbreak
location with high accuracy, requiring only data of N = 4 individuals. The method can
be applied to scenarios with multiple outbreak locations, and is even able to estimate
the number of outbreak sources if unknown, while being robust to noise. Our
method is the first to offer a reliable, accurate out-of-the-box approach to identify
outbreak locations in the initial phase of an outbreak. It can be easily and quickly
applied in a crisis situation, improving on previous manual approaches. The method is
not only applicable in the context of disease outbreaks, but can be used to find
shared locations in movement data in other contexts as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Monitor: Contact patterns during the Pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/contact_monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/contact_monitor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to mobility, we now show the average contacts in the population over time—with equally important insights into the course of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mobility of people gives us an important overview of the pandemic, but it is actually the contacts between people that are instrumental in the infection dynamics: Transmissions occur when people meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the new &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/contact-index/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;contact monitor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we make these contacts visible. The monitor shows the average number of contacts that a person in Germany had on a given day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can clearly see how strongly contacts have decreased in March 2020, and how they are still at a low level more than a year after the start of the pandemic. Also visible are the different phases of the pandemic and reactions to it with lockdowns, relaxations, holidays and vacations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of contacts is calculated from GPS mobile phone data and provided to us as an anonymous, aggregated statistic - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/data-info/contacts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;more on the methodology here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will continue to analyze contact dynamics and investigate what conclusions can be drawn about infection dynamics. For example, in the study &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/118/31/e2026731118&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ruediger et al.&lt;/a&gt;, contacts were shown to be related to the reproductive number R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-potential/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-potential/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are happy that our preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2102.13600.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is out and available on &lt;em&gt;arxiv.org&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a very constructive and effective collaborative effort, lead by our &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/author/dr.-benjamin-f.-maier/&#34;&gt;Ben Maier&lt;/a&gt;, who did all the heavy lifting, and valuable contributions by the teams of Cornelia Betsch, Michael Meyer-Hermann and by Karl Lauterbach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell we evaluate and compare different vaccination strageties of COVID-19 mRNA-vaccines in high-risk groups in Germany and show that a flexible scheduling of the second vaccine dose can potentially be the way to go. If you are interested in the details, have a look at the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vaccination against COVID-19 with the recently approved mRNA vaccines BNT162b2 (BioNTech/Pfizer) and mRNA-1273 (Moderna) is currently underway in a large number of countries. However, high incidence rates and rapidly spreading SARS-CoV-2 variants are concerning. In combination with acute supply deficits in Europe in early 2021, the question arises of whether stretching the vaccine, for instance by delaying the second dose, can make a significant contribution to preventing deaths, despite associated risks such as lower vaccine efficacy, the potential emergence of escape mutants, enhancement, waning immunity, reduced social acceptance of off-label vaccination, and liability shifts. A quantitative epidemiological assessment of risks and benefits of non-standard vaccination protocols remains elusive. To clarify the situation and to provide a quantitative epidemiological foundation we develop a stochastic epidemiological model that integrates specific vaccine rollout protocols into a risk-group structured infectious disease dynamical model. Using the situation and conditions in Germany as a reference system, we show that delaying the second vaccine dose is expected to prevent deaths in the four to five digit range, should the incidence resurge. We show that this considerable public health benefit relies on the fact that both mRNA vaccines provide substantial protection against severe COVID-19 and death beginning 12 to 14 days after the first dose. The benefits of protocol change are attenuated should vaccine compliance decrease substantially. To quantify the impact of protocol change on vaccination adherence we performed a large-scale online survey. We find that, in Germany, changing vaccination protocols may lead to small reductions in vaccination intention. In sum, we therefore expect the benefits of a strategy change to remain substantial and stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 lockdown induces disease-mitigating structural changes in mobility networks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2020-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2020-covid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>German COVID-19 Snapshot Monitoring (COSMO)-Welle 11 (12.05.2020)</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/betsch-2020-kosmo-welle11/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/betsch-2020-kosmo-welle11/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>German COVID-19 Snapshot Monitoring (COSMO)-Welle 9 (28.04.2020)</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/betsch-2020-kosmo-welle9/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/betsch-2020-kosmo-welle9/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
