<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Old News | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/old_news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Old News</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>Old News</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out: Understanding the impact of digital contact tracing during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dct-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dct-paper/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out: Germany’s fourth COVID-19 wave was mainly driven by the unvaccinated</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/role_of_vaccinated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/role_of_vaccinated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s43856-022-00176-7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In this paper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we use a recently developed approach (the contribution matrix method) in combination with epidemiological data to estimate the contribution of vaccinated and unvaccinated populations to the current COVID-19 effective reproduction number &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt; in Germany. We find that a substantial fraction of reproduction is caused by unvaccinated individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pdf of the paper is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s43856-022-00176-7.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the majority of the German population was fully vaccinated at the time (about 65%), COVID-19 incidence started growing exponentially in October 2021 with about 41% of recorded new cases aged twelve or above being symptomatic breakthrough infections, presumably also contributing to the dynamics. So far, it remained elusive how significant this contribution was and whether targeted non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) may have stopped the amplification of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We develop and introduce a contribution matrix approach based on the next-generation matrix of a population-structured compartmental infectious disease model to derive contributions of respective inter- and intragroup infection pathways of unvaccinated and vaccinated subpopulations to the effective reproduction number and new infections, considering empirical data of vaccine efficacies against infection and transmission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we show that about 61%–76% of all new infections were caused by unvaccinated individuals and only 24%–39% were caused by the vaccinated. Furthermore, 32%–51% of new infections were likely caused by unvaccinated infecting other unvaccinated. Decreasing the transmissibility of the unvaccinated by, e. g. targeted NPIs, causes a steeper decrease in the effective reproduction number R than decreasing the transmissibility of vaccinated individuals, potentially leading to temporary epidemic control. Reducing contacts between vaccinated and unvaccinated individuals serves to decrease R in a similar manner as increasing vaccine uptake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A minority of the German population—the unvaccinated—is assumed to have caused the majority of new infections in the fall of 2021 in Germany. Our results highlight the importance of combined measures, such as vaccination campaigns and targeted contact reductions to achieve temporary epidemic control.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Podcast: Das neue Berlin</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/das_neue_berlin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/das_neue_berlin/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dirk  @ Viertausendhertz Podcast</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_4000hz/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_4000hz/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Enhancing global preparedness during an ongoing pandemic from partial and noisy data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is testing at home sufficient? Self tests and official statistics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/datenspende_blog_incidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/datenspende_blog_incidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Preprint Out: Modeling the impact of the Omicron infection wave in Germany</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2021, the first case of SARS-CoV-2 “variant of concern” (VOC) B.1.1.529 (“Omicron”) was reported in Germany, alongside global reports of reduced vaccine efficacy against infections with this variant. The potential threat posed by the rapid spread of this variant in Germany remained, at the time, elusive.
We developed a variant-dependent population-averaged susceptible-exposed-infected-recovered (SEIR) infectious disease model. The model was calibrated on the observed fixation dynamics of the Omicron variant in December 2021, and allowed us to estimate potential courses of upcoming infection waves in Germany, focusing on the corresponding burden on intensive care units (ICUs) and the efficacy of contact reduction strategies. A maximum median incidence of approximately 300 000 (50% PI in 1000: [181,454], 95% PI in 1000: [55,804]) reported cases per day was expected with the median peak occurring in the mid of February 2022, reaching a cumulative Omicron case count of 16.5 million (50% PI in mio: [11.4, 21.3], 95% PI in mio: [4.1, 27.9]) until Apr 1, 2022. These figures were in line with the actual Omicron waves that were subsequently observed in Germany with respective peaks occurring in mid February (peak: 191k daily new cases) and mid March (peak: 230k daily new cases), cumulatively infecting 14.8 million individuals during the study period. The model peak incidence was observed to be highly sensitive to variations in the assumed generation time and decreased with shorter generation time. Low contact reductions were expected to lead to containment. Early, strict, and short contact reductions could have led to a strong “rebound” effect with high incidences after the end of the respective non-pharmaceutical interventions. Higher vaccine uptake would have led to a lower outbreak size. To ensure that ICU occupancy remained below maximum capacity, a relative risk of requiring ICU care of 10%–20% was necessary (after infection with Omicron vs. infection with Delta).
We expected a large cumulative number of infections with the VOC Omicron in Germany with ICU occupancy likely remaining below capacity nevertheless, even without additional non-pharmaceutical interventions. Our estimates were in line with the retrospectively observed waves. The results presented here informed legislation in Germany. The methodology developed in this study might be used to estimate the impact of future waves of COVID-19 or other infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dirk  @ re:publica 22</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_re_publica/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_re_publica/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Podcast: Let&#39;s talk change</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/lets_talk_change/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/lets_talk_change/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint: Estimating the distribution of COVID-19-susceptible, -recovered, and -vaccinated individuals in Germany up to April 2022</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/sero_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/sero_preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.04.19.22274030v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.04.19.22274030v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint: Evidence for positive long- and short-term effects of vaccinations against COVID-19 in wearable sensor metrics -- Insights from the German Corona Data Donation Project</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/long_covid_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/long_covid_preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we use physiological data collected in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.de/science/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;German Data Donation Project (Datenspende)&lt;/a&gt; to investigate the differential impact of vaccination on the effect that a COVID-19 infection has on &lt;strong&gt;resting heart rate&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;physical activity&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sleep&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02846&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02846&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint: Rhythm of relationships in a social fish over the course of a full year in the wild</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/aslak-rhythm-preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/aslak-rhythm-preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.03.11.483964v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.03.11.483964v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out: Finding disease outbreak locations from human mobility data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/outbreak_detection/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/outbreak_detection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we investigated how much information on individual mobility patterns is required
to reconstruct the origin of an outbreak from spatially distributed cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out: not so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://epjdatascience.springeropen.com/articles/10.1140/epjds/s13688-021-00306-6#citeas&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding the origin location of an infectious disease outbreak quickly is crucial in
mitigating its further dissemination. Current methods to identify outbreak locations
early on rely on interviewing affected individuals and correlating their movements,
which is a manual, time-consuming, and error-prone process. Other methods such as
contact tracing, genomic sequencing or theoretical models of epidemic spread offer
help, but they are not applicable at the onset of an outbreak as they require highly
processed information or established transmission chains. Digital data sources such as
mobile phones offer new ways to find outbreak sources in an automated way. Here,
we propose a novel method to determine outbreak origins from geolocated
movement data of individuals affected by the outbreak. Our algorithm scans
movement trajectories for shared locations and identifies the outbreak origin as the
most dominant among them. We test the method using various empirical and
synthetic datasets, and demonstrate that it is able to single out the true outbreak
location with high accuracy, requiring only data of N = 4 individuals. The method can
be applied to scenarios with multiple outbreak locations, and is even able to estimate
the number of outbreak sources if unknown, while being robust to noise. Our
method is the first to offer a reliable, accurate out-of-the-box approach to identify
outbreak locations in the initial phase of an outbreak. It can be easily and quickly
applied in a crisis situation, improving on previous manual approaches. The method is
not only applicable in the context of disease outbreaks, but can be used to find
shared locations in movement data in other contexts as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Monitor: Contact patterns during the Pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/contact_monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/contact_monitor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to mobility, we now show the average contacts in the population over time—with equally important insights into the course of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mobility of people gives us an important overview of the pandemic, but it is actually the contacts between people that are instrumental in the infection dynamics: Transmissions occur when people meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the new &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/contact-index/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;contact monitor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we make these contacts visible. The monitor shows the average number of contacts that a person in Germany had on a given day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can clearly see how strongly contacts have decreased in March 2020, and how they are still at a low level more than a year after the start of the pandemic. Also visible are the different phases of the pandemic and reactions to it with lockdowns, relaxations, holidays and vacations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of contacts is calculated from GPS mobile phone data and provided to us as an anonymous, aggregated statistic - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/data-info/contacts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;more on the methodology here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will continue to analyze contact dynamics and investigate what conclusions can be drawn about infection dynamics. For example, in the study &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/118/31/e2026731118&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ruediger et al.&lt;/a&gt;, contacts were shown to be related to the reproductive number R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dirk&#39;s book is out</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirks_book_out/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirks_book_out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Im Wald vor lauter Bäumen - unsere komplexe Welt besser verstehen&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; is now out and available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This popular scientific book explains the science of Complexity, how it works, what anti-disciplinary science looks like and what benefits are gained by connecting different phenomena observed in traditionally distant scientific disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book captures topics such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;complex networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;synchronization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;critical phenomena&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tipping points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the emergence of cooperation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and illustrates the connections between these phenomena using various examples from biology, ecology and social science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is in German.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information, also in German is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dtv.de/buch/dirk-brockmann-im-wald-vor-lauter-baeumen-28299/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Digital contact tracing contributes little to COVID-19 outbreak containment</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/tracing_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/tracing_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our preprint &amp;ldquo;Digital contact tracing contributes little to COVID-19 outbreak containment&amp;rdquo; is out and available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As digital contact tracing apps raised the hope that they may be efficient enough to contain outbreaks
without falling back to harsher NPIs, we analyzed its success. Relying on empirical results, we find
an expected outbreak size reduction on the order of a few percent at best. While the intervention
may aid the manual tracing process, we argue that countries should concentrate on other means to contain
COVID-19 outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital contact tracing applications have been introduced in many countries to aid in the containment of
COVID-19 outbreaks. Initially, enthusiasm was high regarding their implementation as a non-pharmaceutical
intervention (NPI). Yet, no country was able to prevent larger outbreaks without falling back to harsher NPIs,
and the total effect of digital contact tracing remains elusive. Based on the results of empirical studies and
modeling efforts, we show that digital contact tracing apps might have prevented cases on the order of single-digit
percentages up until now, at best. We show that this poor impact can be attributed to a combination of low
participation rates, a non-flexible reliance on symptom-based testing, low engagement of participants, and
delays between testing and test result upload. We find that contact tracing does not change the epidemic
threshold and exclusively prevents more cases during the supercritical phase of an epidemic, making it unfit
as a tool to prevent outbreaks. Locally clustered contact structures may increase the intervention’s efficacy,
but only if the number of contacts per individual is homogeneously distributed, a condition usually not found in
contact networks.  Our results suggest that policy makers cannot rely on digital contact tracing to contain
outbreaks of COVID-19 or similar diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The ROCS-Team welcomes new members!</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/welcome_new_members/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/welcome_new_members/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our team keeps growing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We warmly welcome:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adrian Pelcaru&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul Buttkus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tashin Talbot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marc Wiedemann&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jakob Kolb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are very happy that they are on board. Welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dirk  @ Jung &amp; Naiv - Folge 503</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_jung_und_naiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_jung_und_naiv/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new COVID-19 mobility monitor report ist online</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/mobility_between_counties/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/mobility_between_counties/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You can find the whole report here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/reports/traffic-grid/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;** -&amp;gt; Traffic Between Adjacent Counties &amp;lt;- **&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/reports/adjacent-travel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;found on the covid-19-mobility monitor site&lt;/a&gt; but is also available as an &lt;a href=&#34;https://observablehq.com/@adrianzachariae/traffic-lattice-germany&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Observable notebook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are happy that our preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2102.13600.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is out and available on &lt;em&gt;arxiv.org&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a very constructive and effective collaborative effort, lead by our &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/author/dr.-benjamin-f.-maier/&#34;&gt;Ben Maier&lt;/a&gt;, who did all the heavy lifting, and valuable contributions by the teams of Cornelia Betsch, Michael Meyer-Hermann and by Karl Lauterbach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell we evaluate and compare different vaccination strageties of COVID-19 mRNA-vaccines in high-risk groups in Germany and show that a flexible scheduling of the second vaccine dose can potentially be the way to go. If you are interested in the details, have a look at the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vaccination against COVID-19 with the recently approved mRNA vaccines BNT162b2 (BioNTech/Pfizer) and mRNA-1273 (Moderna) is currently underway in a large number of countries. However, high incidence rates and rapidly spreading SARS-CoV-2 variants are concerning. In combination with acute supply deficits in Europe in early 2021, the question arises of whether stretching the vaccine, for instance by delaying the second dose, can make a significant contribution to preventing deaths, despite associated risks such as lower vaccine efficacy, the potential emergence of escape mutants, enhancement, waning immunity, reduced social acceptance of off-label vaccination, and liability shifts. A quantitative epidemiological assessment of risks and benefits of non-standard vaccination protocols remains elusive. To clarify the situation and to provide a quantitative epidemiological foundation we develop a stochastic epidemiological model that integrates specific vaccine rollout protocols into a risk-group structured infectious disease dynamical model. Using the situation and conditions in Germany as a reference system, we show that delaying the second vaccine dose is expected to prevent deaths in the four to five digit range, should the incidence resurge. We show that this considerable public health benefit relies on the fact that both mRNA vaccines provide substantial protection against severe COVID-19 and death beginning 12 to 14 days after the first dose. The benefits of protocol change are attenuated should vaccine compliance decrease substantially. To quantify the impact of protocol change on vaccination adherence we performed a large-scale online survey. We find that, in Germany, changing vaccination protocols may lead to small reductions in vaccination intention. In sum, we therefore expect the benefits of a strategy change to remain substantial and stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just published: Social networks predict the life and death of honey bees</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/bee_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/bee_paper/</guid>
      <description>






  
    


&lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

   
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/publication/wild-2020-social/&#34;&gt;Social networks predict the life and death of honey bees&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    
  &lt;span &gt;
  B Wild&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  D M Dormagen&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/authors/adrian/&#34;&gt;A Zachariae&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  M L Smith&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  K S Traynor&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/authors/dirk/&#34;&gt;D Brockmann&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  I D Couzin&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  T Landgraf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span
  &gt;&lt;br /&gt;
   Nature Communications 12, 1110
   (2021).
  &lt;p&gt;








  
    
  



&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-21212-5.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  PDF
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm js-cite-modal&#34;
        data-filename=&#34;/publication/wild-2020-social/cite.bib&#34;&gt;
  Cite
&lt;/a&gt;













&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21212-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  DOI
&lt;/a&gt;



  
  
  
    
  
  
  
  
  
    
  
  &lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-21212-5#citeas&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
    View&lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/p&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

  


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pascal Klamser joins the ROCS-Team - Welcome Pascal</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/welcom_pascal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/welcom_pascal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Pascal is a physicist by training with a PhD (almost) in biophysics and an interdisciplinary interest with a focus on multi-agent systems. How simple interaction rules shape the large scale dynamics of a system is the unifying question behind diverse projects as predator avoidance in collective behavior and opinion dynamics on adaptive networks. He joined our team during the Corona pandemic in March 2021.
&lt;p&gt;In our team Pascal will expand our COVID-19 modeling efforts. He will also dive into the data analytics projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are very happy that Pascal will be joining us soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new COVID-19 mobility monitor report ist online</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/new_mobility_report/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/new_mobility_report/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You can find the whole report here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/reports/adjacent-travel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;** -&amp;gt; Traffic in the Pandemic by Distance &amp;lt;- **&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In past reports we have shown repeatedly that the change in mobility during the pandemic affects local and long-distance traffic differently. Recently, there has been increased interest in traffic-by-distance, as actual and proposed policies like the “15-km rule” have targeted long-distance travel to limit the spread from COVID-19 hotspots to neighboring areas and beyond. This report explores &lt;strong&gt;how much traffic remains local&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;how much crosses borders&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;how drastic regional differences are&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/reports/adjacent-travel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;found on the covid-19-mobility monitor site&lt;/a&gt; but is also available as an &lt;a href=&#34;https://observablehq.com/@adrianzachariae/traffic-in-the-pandemic-by-distance&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Observable notebook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dirk Brockmann macht Schule</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_9th_grade/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_9th_grade/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
