<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kamil Fuławka | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/kamil/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/authors/kamil/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Kamil Fuławka</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/authors/kamil/avatar_hueaffc988be1310b04c8e1596ab7cc80f_344026_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Kamil Fuławka</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/kamil/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How people say they feel about uncertainty does not match how they decide</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/computational_psychiatry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/computational_psychiatry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kamil Fuławka from our Computational Social Science group, together with colleagues Yannik Paul and Anya Pedersen from Kiel University, has published a new article in &lt;em&gt;Computational Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt;. The study &lt;em&gt;“Decomposing Intolerance of Uncertainty: No Association With Affective Decision Making in a Community Sample”&lt;/em&gt; addresses a central question in psychology: &lt;strong&gt;How do people respond to uncertainty, and what drives these responses?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intolerance of uncertainty (IU) is considered a key factor across many psychological disorders, from anxiety to obsessive-compulsive symptoms. Yet the mechanisms behind it remain unclear. To explore this, the authors identified three possible pathways: overweighting negative outcomes, distorting probabilities of rare events, and discomfort with missing information. They then mapped these mechanisms onto well-known patterns of human decision-making described by Cumulative Prospect Theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test this link, the team designed an experiment with 100 participants. Instead of abstract lotteries with money, they used medical scenarios in which people had to choose between two hypothetical painkillers, each with possible side effects and varying chances of success. In one condition, all information was provided upfront. In the other, participants had to discover probabilities by sampling outcomes themselves. This allowed the researchers to compare decision-making under risk with decision-making under uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results confirmed that participants displayed common biases: they overweighed side effects compared to benefits (loss aversion), and they distorted small probabilities. Choices also differed depending on whether information was described or experienced, echoing the well-known description–experience gap. However, none of these behavioral patterns correlated with how strongly individuals reported disliking uncertainty on questionnaires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This finding is important because it suggests that self-reported intolerance of uncertainty and observable decision-making behavior may capture different aspects of the phenomenon. The study points to the need for more precise definitions of IU and for experimental designs that can create stronger affective contexts, possibly with real consequences for behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://cpsyjournal.org/articles/10.5334/cpsy.140&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the full article here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decomposing Intolerance of Uncertainty: No Association With Affective Decision Making in a Community Sample</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/kamil-2025-decomposing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/kamil-2025-decomposing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large language models accurately identify decision reasons in verbal reports</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/kamil-2025-llms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/kamil-2025-llms/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint on decision-making and large language models</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/preprint-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/preprint-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our colleague &lt;strong&gt;Kamil Fulawka&lt;/strong&gt; is the first author of a new preprint investigating how large language models (LLMs) can be used to understand the psychology of risky choice. Together with &lt;strong&gt;Ralph Hertwig&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Dirk Wulff&lt;/strong&gt;, he introduces a scalable approach to analyze participants’ free-text explanations of their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study shows that LLMs can accurately identify the reasons people give for their lottery choices in more than &lt;strong&gt;92% of cases&lt;/strong&gt;. These verbal reports reveal systematic patterns: people’s reasoning depends strongly on the &lt;strong&gt;structure of the choice problem&lt;/strong&gt; rather than being fixed across individuals. Models based on these reason profiles also achieve &lt;strong&gt;higher predictive accuracy than prospect theory&lt;/strong&gt;, one of the most established frameworks in decision science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By demonstrating the &lt;strong&gt;scientific value of verbal data&lt;/strong&gt;, the work opens new avenues for developing context-aware models of human decision-making. We are proud of Kamil’s contribution to this important line of research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/yuzmw_v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the preprint here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Statistical Modeling for Online Behavior Data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/teaching/stats_model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/teaching/stats_model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Opal: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bildungsportal.sachsen.de/opal/auth/RepositoryEntry/48880648204/CourseNode/1743474776839555003&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time Thursdays, 5. DS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location BAR/0I89&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Department Computer Science&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modules INF-BAS3 (Software- und Web-Engineering)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language English&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assessment oral exam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online platforms generate vast amounts of behavioral data, including subjective ratings (e.g., likes, stars, reactions) and objective engagement metrics (e.g., views, clicks, watch time). While machine learning excels at predicting user behavior, statistical modeling—a cornerstone of empirical research—is critical for interpretable analysis. It helps uncover relationships between user behavior and various factors (e.g., how demographics influence engagement patterns) and enables causal inference in experiments (e.g., measuring the impact of different feed-ranking algorithms on user experience). These methods are widely used in UX research, product analytics, and A/B testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course provides a hands-on introduction to statistical modeling in R, focusing on methods most useful for analyzing behavioral data. We&amp;rsquo;ll cover key concepts and progress to model selection based on outcome type. Topics include logistic regression for binary outcomes (e.g., like/dislike reactions), ordinal regression for rating scales, beta regression for continuous feedback (e.g., sliders), and hierarchical models for nested data (e.g., multiple ratings from the same users). In the end, you&amp;rsquo;ll not only know which model to use but also how to effectively visualize and communicate your findings through clear, interpretable result presentations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No prior statistical modeling experience is required. If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with Python or similar languages, the transition to R should be easy. All scripts and exercises are provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;schedule&#34;&gt;Schedule:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 1: General Introduction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 1 Introduction to statistical modeling: goals and principles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 2 Linear regression: the foundational model, applications and limitations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 2: Selected Generalized Linear Models&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 1 Logistic regression 1: analysis of likes and dislikes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 2 Logistic regression 2: multivariate analysis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 3 Ordinal regression 1: stars and other likert-type ratings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 4 Ordinal regression 2: modeling distributional parameters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 5 Beta regression 1: slider-type ratings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 6 Beta regression 2: modeling distributional parameters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 7 Interim summary, additional exercises, and other GLMs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 3: Experimental design &amp;amp; hierarchical models&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 1 Modeling between- and within-individual experimental designs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 2 Hierarchical models 1: introduction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 3 Hierarchical models 2: logistic and ordinal regression&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 4 Hierarchical models 3: Beta regression&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 5 Final session, Q&amp;amp;A, discussion and feedback&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
