<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Annika Rose | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/annika/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/authors/annika/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Annika Rose</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/authors/annika/avatar_huab55308732bec8bc9f633b3be541197c_131638_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Annika Rose</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/annika/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint on large-scale wearable sleep data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/sleep_data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/sleep_data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our colleague &lt;strong&gt;Annika Rose&lt;/strong&gt; is the lead author of a new preprint that analyzes the largest dataset on sleep ever collected in Germany. The study &lt;em&gt;“Large-scale wearable data reveal spatiotemporal organization of annual sleep patterns”&lt;/em&gt; is available on &lt;strong&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/strong&gt; and is currently being revised for submission to &lt;strong&gt;Nature Communications&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Annika and her team analyzed more than &lt;strong&gt;45 million nights of sleep data&lt;/strong&gt; from over &lt;strong&gt;100,000 people&lt;/strong&gt; collected in the Robert Koch Institute’s Corona Data Donation project. The results show clear &lt;strong&gt;east–west and north–south differences&lt;/strong&gt; in sleep: people in western Germany go to bed and wake up later than those in the east. In the north, people sleep less and experience stronger social jetlag. The study also identifies strong &lt;strong&gt;seasonal rhythms&lt;/strong&gt;, with longer sleep in winter and shorter sleep in summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond these regional findings, the study demonstrates how &lt;strong&gt;large-scale wearable data&lt;/strong&gt; can serve as a framework to understand circadian regulation at the population level. This perspective highlights both the broader scientific relevance of the work and its potential applications beyond Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.08.03.668323&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the preprint here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal Organization of Sleep</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/spatiotemporal-sleep-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/spatiotemporal-sleep-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We perform comprehensive spatiotemporal analyses of sleep patterns in a sample of over 100,000 individuals across Germany spanning almost 3 years. As part of the Robert Koch Institute&amp;rsquo;s Data Donation Project for the early detection of COVID-19, sleep data, in conjunction with heart rate and activity data, was collected in a privacy-preserving fashion by passive sensors in consumer wearable devices from April 2020 until December 2022, yielding more than 45 million nights of sleep observations overall. Sleep tracking studies for the first time enable a means of large-scale, real-time, non-invasive, continuous, longitudinal objective sleep measurements at a relatively low-cost with high accessibility. This combination of long observation period, and high temporal and spatial resolution is ideally suited to track sleep behavior over time, enabling the identification of robust seasonal trends as well as fine-grained analyses of short-term changes. The large number of regular participants from all over Germany allows for spatial analyses in a highly-resolved manner to discern complex patterns along geographical position or population density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure style=&#34;margin-top: 0;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;!-- &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/sleep.html&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;Full&#34;/&gt; --&gt;
 &lt;iframe src=&#34;./sleep.html&#34; width=&#34;1000px&#34; height=&#34;795px&#34; margin-top=&#39;0&#39; style=&#34;border:none;&#34; overflow:hidden;&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
 &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
Spatiotemporal analyses of sleep behavior have great informative value for public health. Mapping sleep patterns is essential to understanding which external conditions pose risks for sleep, which ones may be protective, and how these conditions interact. The two main conditions that we focus on are in constant conflict with each other in our modern lives: - Sun time (or solar time) refers to the natural time structure on Earth based on the position of the sun in the sky, which gives rise to the timing and duration of day and night as well as the seasons. - Social time (or societal time) refers to the human-constructed timing framework, shaped by policy and social forces, that determines weekly structure, work and school schedules, time zone allocation and adherence to daylight saving time.
&lt;p&gt;Individual aspects of this interaction of sun and social time on sleep and circadian rhythms have been investigated in numerous studies to date. These studies range from small diary studies and detailed physiological studies in small but high-quality samples to large questionnaire-based studies, with studies based on wearable sensor data in larger samples a most recent addition. Their seemingly conflicting results on the relative contribution of social and sun time and the seasonality of human sleep highlight the complexity of the matter at hand. Moreover, it indicates the biological and epidemiological insights that may be gleaned from assessing systematic patterns in sleep with season, weekly structure and geographical position to pinpoint vulnerable populations and effective countermeasures where sun and social time conflicts may lead to unfavorable sleep outcomes and risks for acute and long-term health and safety may arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Corona Data Donation project, we were able to assess many of the social and solar attributes of sleep for the first time together in one large, longitudinal data set of objective sleep phenotypes. Our results emphasize the effectiveness of passive sensing for monitoring and understanding trends in public health.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;!-- &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;!-- &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/sleep.html&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;Full&#34;/&gt; --&gt;
 &lt;!-- &lt;iframe src=&#34;./figures/sleep.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;100%&#34; style=&#34;border:none;&#34; overflow:hidden;&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; --&gt;
  &lt;!-- &lt;figcaption&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;/figcaption&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;/figure&gt; --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for positive long- and short-term effects of vaccinations against COVID-19 in wearable sensor metrics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/wiedermann-2023-evidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/wiedermann-2023-evidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the impact of the Omicron infection wave in Germany</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-modeling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the share of SARS-CoV-2- immunologically naïve individuals in Germany up to June 2022</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-estimating/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-estimating/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is testing at home sufficient? Self tests and official statistics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/datenspende_blog_incidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/datenspende_blog_incidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Preprint Out: Modeling the impact of the Omicron infection wave in Germany</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2021, the first case of SARS-CoV-2 “variant of concern” (VOC) B.1.1.529 (“Omicron”) was reported in Germany, alongside global reports of reduced vaccine efficacy against infections with this variant. The potential threat posed by the rapid spread of this variant in Germany remained, at the time, elusive.
We developed a variant-dependent population-averaged susceptible-exposed-infected-recovered (SEIR) infectious disease model. The model was calibrated on the observed fixation dynamics of the Omicron variant in December 2021, and allowed us to estimate potential courses of upcoming infection waves in Germany, focusing on the corresponding burden on intensive care units (ICUs) and the efficacy of contact reduction strategies. A maximum median incidence of approximately 300 000 (50% PI in 1000: [181,454], 95% PI in 1000: [55,804]) reported cases per day was expected with the median peak occurring in the mid of February 2022, reaching a cumulative Omicron case count of 16.5 million (50% PI in mio: [11.4, 21.3], 95% PI in mio: [4.1, 27.9]) until Apr 1, 2022. These figures were in line with the actual Omicron waves that were subsequently observed in Germany with respective peaks occurring in mid February (peak: 191k daily new cases) and mid March (peak: 230k daily new cases), cumulatively infecting 14.8 million individuals during the study period. The model peak incidence was observed to be highly sensitive to variations in the assumed generation time and decreased with shorter generation time. Low contact reductions were expected to lead to containment. Early, strict, and short contact reductions could have led to a strong “rebound” effect with high incidences after the end of the respective non-pharmaceutical interventions. Higher vaccine uptake would have led to a lower outbreak size. To ensure that ICU occupancy remained below maximum capacity, a relative risk of requiring ICU care of 10%–20% was necessary (after infection with Omicron vs. infection with Delta).
We expected a large cumulative number of infections with the VOC Omicron in Germany with ICU occupancy likely remaining below capacity nevertheless, even without additional non-pharmaceutical interventions. Our estimates were in line with the retrospectively observed waves. The results presented here informed legislation in Germany. The methodology developed in this study might be used to estimate the impact of future waves of COVID-19 or other infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint: Estimating the distribution of COVID-19-susceptible, -recovered, and -vaccinated individuals in Germany up to April 2022</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/sero_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/sero_preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.04.19.22274030v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.04.19.22274030v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint: Evidence for positive long- and short-term effects of vaccinations against COVID-19 in wearable sensor metrics -- Insights from the German Corona Data Donation Project</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/long_covid_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/long_covid_preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we use physiological data collected in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.de/science/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;German Data Donation Project (Datenspende)&lt;/a&gt; to investigate the differential impact of vaccination on the effect that a COVID-19 infection has on &lt;strong&gt;resting heart rate&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;physical activity&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sleep&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02846&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02846&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-potential/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-potential/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are happy that our preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2102.13600.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is out and available on &lt;em&gt;arxiv.org&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a very constructive and effective collaborative effort, lead by our &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/author/dr.-benjamin-f.-maier/&#34;&gt;Ben Maier&lt;/a&gt;, who did all the heavy lifting, and valuable contributions by the teams of Cornelia Betsch, Michael Meyer-Hermann and by Karl Lauterbach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell we evaluate and compare different vaccination strageties of COVID-19 mRNA-vaccines in high-risk groups in Germany and show that a flexible scheduling of the second vaccine dose can potentially be the way to go. If you are interested in the details, have a look at the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vaccination against COVID-19 with the recently approved mRNA vaccines BNT162b2 (BioNTech/Pfizer) and mRNA-1273 (Moderna) is currently underway in a large number of countries. However, high incidence rates and rapidly spreading SARS-CoV-2 variants are concerning. In combination with acute supply deficits in Europe in early 2021, the question arises of whether stretching the vaccine, for instance by delaying the second dose, can make a significant contribution to preventing deaths, despite associated risks such as lower vaccine efficacy, the potential emergence of escape mutants, enhancement, waning immunity, reduced social acceptance of off-label vaccination, and liability shifts. A quantitative epidemiological assessment of risks and benefits of non-standard vaccination protocols remains elusive. To clarify the situation and to provide a quantitative epidemiological foundation we develop a stochastic epidemiological model that integrates specific vaccine rollout protocols into a risk-group structured infectious disease dynamical model. Using the situation and conditions in Germany as a reference system, we show that delaying the second vaccine dose is expected to prevent deaths in the four to five digit range, should the incidence resurge. We show that this considerable public health benefit relies on the fact that both mRNA vaccines provide substantial protection against severe COVID-19 and death beginning 12 to 14 days after the first dose. The benefits of protocol change are attenuated should vaccine compliance decrease substantially. To quantify the impact of protocol change on vaccination adherence we performed a large-scale online survey. We find that, in Germany, changing vaccination protocols may lead to small reductions in vaccination intention. In sum, we therefore expect the benefits of a strategy change to remain substantial and stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Corona Datenspende App</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/datenspende/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/datenspende/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
