<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>COVID-19 | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/covid-19/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/covid-19/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>COVID-19</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/covid-19/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inferring country-specific import risk of diseases from the world air transportation network</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2024-inferring/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2024-inferring/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal Organization of Sleep</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/spatiotemporal-sleep-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/spatiotemporal-sleep-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We perform comprehensive spatiotemporal analyses of sleep patterns in a sample of over 100,000 individuals across Germany spanning almost 3 years. As part of the Robert Koch Institute&amp;rsquo;s Data Donation Project for the early detection of COVID-19, sleep data, in conjunction with heart rate and activity data, was collected in a privacy-preserving fashion by passive sensors in consumer wearable devices from April 2020 until December 2022, yielding more than 45 million nights of sleep observations overall. Sleep tracking studies for the first time enable a means of large-scale, real-time, non-invasive, continuous, longitudinal objective sleep measurements at a relatively low-cost with high accessibility. This combination of long observation period, and high temporal and spatial resolution is ideally suited to track sleep behavior over time, enabling the identification of robust seasonal trends as well as fine-grained analyses of short-term changes. The large number of regular participants from all over Germany allows for spatial analyses in a highly-resolved manner to discern complex patterns along geographical position or population density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure style=&#34;margin-top: 0;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;!-- &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/sleep.html&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;Full&#34;/&gt; --&gt;
 &lt;iframe src=&#34;./sleep.html&#34; width=&#34;1000px&#34; height=&#34;795px&#34; margin-top=&#39;0&#39; style=&#34;border:none;&#34; overflow:hidden;&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
 &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
Spatiotemporal analyses of sleep behavior have great informative value for public health. Mapping sleep patterns is essential to understanding which external conditions pose risks for sleep, which ones may be protective, and how these conditions interact. The two main conditions that we focus on are in constant conflict with each other in our modern lives: - Sun time (or solar time) refers to the natural time structure on Earth based on the position of the sun in the sky, which gives rise to the timing and duration of day and night as well as the seasons. - Social time (or societal time) refers to the human-constructed timing framework, shaped by policy and social forces, that determines weekly structure, work and school schedules, time zone allocation and adherence to daylight saving time.
&lt;p&gt;Individual aspects of this interaction of sun and social time on sleep and circadian rhythms have been investigated in numerous studies to date. These studies range from small diary studies and detailed physiological studies in small but high-quality samples to large questionnaire-based studies, with studies based on wearable sensor data in larger samples a most recent addition. Their seemingly conflicting results on the relative contribution of social and sun time and the seasonality of human sleep highlight the complexity of the matter at hand. Moreover, it indicates the biological and epidemiological insights that may be gleaned from assessing systematic patterns in sleep with season, weekly structure and geographical position to pinpoint vulnerable populations and effective countermeasures where sun and social time conflicts may lead to unfavorable sleep outcomes and risks for acute and long-term health and safety may arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Corona Data Donation project, we were able to assess many of the social and solar attributes of sleep for the first time together in one large, longitudinal data set of objective sleep phenotypes. Our results emphasize the effectiveness of passive sensing for monitoring and understanding trends in public health.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;!-- &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;!-- &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/sleep.html&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;Full&#34;/&gt; --&gt;
 &lt;!-- &lt;iframe src=&#34;./figures/sleep.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;100%&#34; style=&#34;border:none;&#34; overflow:hidden;&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; --&gt;
  &lt;!-- &lt;figcaption&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;/figcaption&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;/figure&gt; --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 Detection from Wearables</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/covid_detection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/covid_detection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Controlling the spread of infectious diseases early in a pandemic is crucial. The recent COVID-19 outbreak and its rapid global spread highlight the urgent need for tools that can limit the spreading of infectious diseases at the earliest stage possible to prevent global pandemics.
Previous research has suggested the potential to detect COVID-19 infections through the observation of physiological alterations occurring after the onset of the disease, including elevated resting heart rates, extended sleep durations, and decreased physical activity. Wearable sensors, equipped to monitor these changes, in conjunction with machine learning algorithms trained on data from these sensors, could identify these variations, thus providing a method to quickly classify individuals as infected.
Utilizing wearable sensor data from the Corona Data Donation Project, which encompasses resting heart rate, step count, and sleep duration time series from over 120,000 voluntary participants, a Logistic Regression model was developed for the classification of submitted COVID-19 test results. This model achieved classification success, as evidenced by a Receiver Operating Characteristic Area Under the Curve (ROC AUC) of 0.58, precision of 0.26, and recall of 0.54. The implementation of the catch22 feature set for feature extraction from the submitted wearable sensor data enhanced the interpretability of the classification algorithm. It also enables a more detailed analysis of the specific physiological changes used to differentiate individuals testing positive or negative for COVID-19.
This study emphasizes the capability of predicting COVID-19 across large cohorts and underscores the value of employing infectious disease prediction models based on wearable sensor data as an additional public health tool.
&lt;strong&gt;The LR model presented in Fig. 1 demonstrated&lt;/strong&gt; prediction capabilities for COVID-19 test results surpassing random chance, thereby facilitating the early detection of this infectious disease. Additionally, the incorporation of catch22 features into the feature engineering process enhanced the interpretability of the classification decisions made by the model.
The predictive LR model shown in Fig. 1 demonstrated satisfactory performance, notable given the voluntary nature of data submission, the impossibility of verifying correct and constant wear of devices, reliance on daily averages, absence of precise test and symptom onset dates, and the utilization of multiple devices across a broad cohort. The present study introduced a predictive model that has been trained on a considerable cohort size, addressing concerns from existing research about models only trained on significantly smaller cohorts. Additionally, this study tackled the issue of geographic underrepresentation by developing a predictive model for COVID-19 classification with data donated outside the United States, addressing other concerns in existing literature.
Additionally confirmatory models have been developed which showed performances consistent with existing literature, validating its efficacy in confirming COVID-19 infections within this study’s framework. Enhancements in confirmatory capability were noted with the increasing days included after a COVID-19 test submission, indicating that a longer observational period bolsters the model’s confirmatory power. Employing interpretable catch22 feature engineering provided clarity in the classification process and verified that the detected signals coincide with physiological responses to COVID-19 infection, as shown in Fig. 2 and 3. This consistency in signal detection across the models and their alignment with other research accentuates the catch22 features’ ability to accurately capture vital data signals from wearable sensor data. Conclusively, this study proposes a combined approach of catch22 feature engineering and machine learning classification algorithms as an effective strategy in combating the rapid spread of infectious diseases. Highlighting that this methodology could be particulary valuable in the initial stages of a pandemic, where traditional methods might be unavailable. Thus, it offers an essential addition to public health resources. This study stresses the potential of utilizing wearable sensor data, combined with automated feature engineering and machine learning classification algorithms, for the detection and confirmation of diseases like COVID-19. With additional advancements machine learning approaches to detect illnesses like COVID-19 using wearable sensor data could significantly improve the readiness and response to future public health crise&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/paul_w2.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;Full&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 2 - Permutation Feature Importance for the test dataset for the Confirmatory LR: Focusing on features that led to a mean increase in model performance (increase in Geometric Mean (GM)). This represents a selection from the complete set of features. Each box displayed on the dashed line in the plot illustrates the range from the first to the third quartile of the GM reduction observed over 100 iterations for each catch22 feature. The median reduction in GM is denoted by the orange line within each box. The whiskers extend to the most extreme GM reduction value that falls within 1.5 times the interquartile range from the edges of the box. Any outliers are represented by dots.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/paul_w3.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;Full&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 3 - Permutation Feature Importance for the test dataset for the Confirmatory XGBoost Model: Focusing on features that led to a mean increase in model performance (increase in Geometric Mean (GM)). This represents a selection from the complete set of features. Each box displayed on the dashed line in the plot illustrates the range from the first to the third quartile of the GM reduction observed over 100 iterations for each catch22 feature. The median reduction in GM is denoted by the orange line within each box. The whiskers extend to the most extreme GM reduction value that falls within 1.5 times the interquartile range from the edges of the box. Any outliers are represented by dots.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FEDORA Project Secures Funding to Explore Post-COVID Ecological Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/fedora/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/fedora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to announce that our project, “FEDORA - Federated Network Modeling of Ecological Complex Dynamical Patterns in Post-COVID,” has successfully secured funding. This pioneering initiative aims to advance the understanding of how ecological systems are affected by complex dynamical patterns emerging in the aftermath of the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FEDORA project will focus on federated network modeling to examine these complex patterns, particularly those related to wearable technology, sleep, as well as persistent symptoms observed post-COVID. Through a collaborative approach, the project will harness cutting-edge data and modeling techniques to reveal new insights into the long-term impacts of COVID-19 on ecological and human health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our interdisciplinary team will work together to develop groundbreaking models that integrate data from various sources, creating a comprehensive understanding of the interplay between ecological and health dynamics in the post-COVID world. The insights gained from this project will not only contribute to scientific knowledge but also guide future public health strategies and ecological conservation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to sharing more updates as the project progresses and invite the community to stay tuned for further developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;bmftr-logo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;FEDORA Project Logo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FEDORA Project Secures Funding to Explore Post-COVID Ecological Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/fedora/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/fedora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are thrilled to announce that our project, “FEDORA - Federated Network Modeling of Ecological Complex Dynamical Patterns in Post-COVID,” has successfully secured funding. This pioneering initiative aims to advance the understanding of how ecological systems are affected by complex dynamical patterns emerging in the aftermath of the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FEDORA project will focus on federated network modeling to examine these complex patterns, particularly those related to wearable technology, sleep, as well as persistent symptoms observed post-COVID. Through a collaborative approach, the project will harness cutting-edge data and modeling techniques to reveal new insights into the long-term impacts of COVID-19 on ecological and human health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our interdisciplinary team will work together to develop groundbreaking models that integrate data from various sources, creating a comprehensive understanding of the interplay between ecological and health dynamics in the post-COVID world. The insights gained from this project will not only contribute to scientific knowledge but also guide future public health strategies and ecological conservation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to sharing more updates as the project progresses and invite the community to stay tuned for further developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;logo-federal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;FEDORA Project Logo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Import Risk</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/import_risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/import_risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our globalized world is strongly connected, on the small scale by buses, trains, cars, and on the largest, global scale by the Worldwide Air transportation Network (WAN).
It is likely that our connectivity has not reached its peak yet, since for example the number of globally scheduled air passengers increased yearly by about 6% between 2004 and 2019.
The connectivity has immense consequences on the propagation of disease since alongside passengers everything that sticks to them, such as bacteria, viruses, earth clumps beneath their shoes etc. comes with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project crosses the fields of network science, transportation, mobility and disease dynamics and it&amp;rsquo;s an offspring of the idea to not use the conventional distance (in meter, miles, feet &amp;hellip; pick your unit) as a metric but an &lt;strong&gt;effective distance&lt;/strong&gt; that is based on the mobility between regions.
When - $P(B | A)$ is the probability to travel to B from A (which is computed from mobility fluxes) than the effective distance is $ d _{\text{eff}} (A | B) = d_0 - log (P(i| n_0)) $ -.
In the seminal paper by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.1245200&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Brockmann and Helbing (2013)&lt;/a&gt; _effective distance $d _{\text{eff}}$ - was shown to linearly correlate with the arrival time of diseases as shown in Fig. 2.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/eff_dist_paper_adapted_1.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;Full&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 2 - The shortest path tree based on the &lt;b&gt;effective distance&lt;/b&gt; with the airport of Hong Kong as origin (&lt;b&gt;A&lt;/b&gt;) and how a pandemic spreads around the globe (&lt;b&gt;B&lt;/b&gt;).
  While the spread on the world map seems rather random, you see a nice circular wave spreading in the effective distance tree, illustrating the linear correlation to disease arrival times.
  Adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/full/10.1126/science.1245200&#34;&gt;Brockmann and Helbing&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our recent paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011775&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Klamser et al. (2024),&lt;/a&gt; we deepen the connection between the effective distance shortest path tree, spreading dynamics and mobility.
We present a way to estimate the passenger flow between any two airports (including those without direct connections) given that we only know the number and maximal capacity of planes (see illustrative example in Fig. 3).
In the end, the method allows us to estimate the number of infected passenger leaving B when we know the number of infected that entered A.
Thus, we know the risk of importation and why it is named &lt;b&gt;import risk method&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/relrisk.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;400&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 3 - Import Risk Example: 100 infected passengers board planes at airport X en route to destination airports elsewhere in the network, going through transit airports in the process. The relative import risk at a given destination is the fraction of the 100 individuals that entered at airport X and exited at that destination airport (red).
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mechanistic idea behind the import risk method is to let a random walker start at node B of the WAN and exit at each node with a probability derived from the effective distance shortest path tree.
The final fraction of times it leaves at node A is the import risk probability.
Now, this method is parameter free and motivated by disease dynamics, but at the same time it provides a method to estimate mobility on a global scale.
The mobility estimation is a classic task in transportation science with well-established models as the gravity model (proposed in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2087063?casa_token=5goDmVg4aOkAAAAA%3A6Y9zup7UcSjT8DQ1izhRza_-N568nGLP_43ikQys0Vzoux-4qaYKp1u0Cruz2YwZ2hggPU2PIKW4oqbB6xnFtaJIgj-oX_zCbMwLneoPv8OzCdsFXA&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;1946 by Zipf&lt;/a&gt;).
A core aspect of our import risk paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011775&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Klamser et al. (2024)&lt;/a&gt; is to compare our method to established mobility models.
We found that our approach outperforms the established models, and the crazy thing is, that our method is parameter free, while the gravity model always needs parameter estimation (one needs to know the real mobility flow beforehand).
This holds true if we check the prediction quality for the 10 countries with the highest import probability, which is especially important for disease propagation since these countries are the one that should increase their passenger control (shown in Fig. 4).&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/ir_paper_fig_10cntrs.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;800&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Fig. 4 - Mobility model comparisons for top 10 import countries: The well-established gravity model with exponential (&lt;b&gt;A&lt;/b&gt;) and power-law (&lt;b&gt;B&lt;/b&gt;) distance decay, the parameter free radiation model (&lt;b&gt;C&lt;/b&gt;) and our import risk model (&lt;b&gt;D&lt;/b&gt;).
  Each dot is a country that is among the 10 countries with the highest import probability from another country (10 target countries x 183 source countries).
  A true or false positive (T.Pos. or F. Pos.) means that the country is or is not among the 10 countries with the highest reference import probability.
  A false negative (F. Neg.) means that it belongs according to reference it is among the top 10 but was not detected by the respective model.
  Figure adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011775&#34;&gt;Klamser et al. (2024)&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We applied the measure during COVID-19 to estimate the countries that have been reached by Omicron without it being detected &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/reports/importrisk_omicron_update/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
And in a big cooperation with great colleagues that have been put together by &lt;a href=&#34;https://manliodedomenico.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Manlio De Domenico,&lt;/a&gt; we have developed and validated a framework (&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/pnasnexus/article/2/6/pgad192/7191545?login=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Klamser and d&amp;rsquo;Andrea et al. (2023)&lt;/a&gt;)that can estimate from sparse and noisy samples via phylogenetic analysis the time when the variant first occurred in the country of origin, how it spreads across the globe with our import risk model, and how the countries are affected by a disease dynamic model.
We were even able to smash everything into one number, which we call the &lt;strong&gt;pandemic delay&lt;/strong&gt;, that estimates how long it takes for a new emerging variant to make out 10% of all current cases in a respective country.
It revealed that only by combining mobility data with a phylogenetic estimate of the reproduction number, the pandemic potentials of the lineages are correctly
assessed relative to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just published: Using smartphones to study vaccination decisions in the wild</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/smartphones_vaccination_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/smartphones_vaccination_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to share our latest research findings with the community. Recently, we have developed an innovative method in cooperation with the DTU to study how people make vaccination decisions in everyday life. For this purpose, we used a specially designed smartphone app that captures real interactions and allows us to analyze the impact of these interactions on vaccination decisions.
Our findings show that people in real decision-making situations rely more heavily on their personal experiences or personal risk assessments than on what they hear or see from others. This method allows us to better understand decision-making behavior in a real-world context.
We are confident that these new insights will provide valuable input for shaping future vaccination campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the detailed paper here:&lt;/p&gt;







  
    


&lt;div class=&#34;pub-list-item&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 1rem&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

   
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/publication/girardini-2024-understanding/&#34;&gt;Using smartphones to study vaccination decisions in the wild&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;article-metadata li-cite-author&#34;&gt;
    
  &lt;span &gt;
  N A Girardini&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  A Stopczynski&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  O Baranov&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  C Betsch&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/authors/dirk/&#34;&gt;D Brockmann&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  S Lehmann&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span &gt;
  R Böhm&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span
  &gt;&lt;br /&gt;
   PLOS Digital Health 3(8): e0000550
   (2024).
  &lt;p&gt;








  

















&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pdig.0000550&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  DOI
&lt;/a&gt;



  
  
  
    
  
  
  
  
  
    
  
  &lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/digitalhealth/article?id=10.1371/journal.pdig.0000550&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
    View&lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/p&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

  


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using smartphones to study vaccination decisions in the wild</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/girardini-2024-understanding/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/girardini-2024-understanding/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citizen data sovereignty is key to wearables and wellness data reuse for the common good</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/gilbert-2024-citizen/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/gilbert-2024-citizen/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for positive long- and short-term effects of vaccinations against COVID-19 in wearable sensor metrics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/wiedermann-2023-evidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/wiedermann-2023-evidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing global preparedness during an ongoing pandemic from partial and noisy data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2023-enhancing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2023-enhancing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the impact of the Omicron infection wave in Germany</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-modeling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the share of SARS-CoV-2- immunologically naïve individuals in Germany up to June 2022</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-estimating/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-estimating/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing and predicting the spatial evolution of Carbapenemase-producing Enterobacteriaceae outbreaks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/myall-2023-reconstructing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/myall-2023-reconstructing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From delta to omicron: The role of individual factors and social context in self-reported compliance with pandemic regulations and recommendations</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/sprengholz-2023-fromdelta/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/sprengholz-2023-fromdelta/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out: Understanding the impact of digital contact tracing during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dct-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dct-paper/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the impact of digital contact tracing during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/burdinski-2021-tracing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/burdinski-2021-tracing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out: Germany’s fourth COVID-19 wave was mainly driven by the unvaccinated</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/role_of_vaccinated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/role_of_vaccinated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s43856-022-00176-7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In this paper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we use a recently developed approach (the contribution matrix method) in combination with epidemiological data to estimate the contribution of vaccinated and unvaccinated populations to the current COVID-19 effective reproduction number &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt; in Germany. We find that a substantial fraction of reproduction is caused by unvaccinated individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pdf of the paper is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s43856-022-00176-7.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the majority of the German population was fully vaccinated at the time (about 65%), COVID-19 incidence started growing exponentially in October 2021 with about 41% of recorded new cases aged twelve or above being symptomatic breakthrough infections, presumably also contributing to the dynamics. So far, it remained elusive how significant this contribution was and whether targeted non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) may have stopped the amplification of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We develop and introduce a contribution matrix approach based on the next-generation matrix of a population-structured compartmental infectious disease model to derive contributions of respective inter- and intragroup infection pathways of unvaccinated and vaccinated subpopulations to the effective reproduction number and new infections, considering empirical data of vaccine efficacies against infection and transmission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we show that about 61%–76% of all new infections were caused by unvaccinated individuals and only 24%–39% were caused by the vaccinated. Furthermore, 32%–51% of new infections were likely caused by unvaccinated infecting other unvaccinated. Decreasing the transmissibility of the unvaccinated by, e. g. targeted NPIs, causes a steeper decrease in the effective reproduction number R than decreasing the transmissibility of vaccinated individuals, potentially leading to temporary epidemic control. Reducing contacts between vaccinated and unvaccinated individuals serves to decrease R in a similar manner as increasing vaccine uptake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A minority of the German population—the unvaccinated—is assumed to have caused the majority of new infections in the fall of 2021 in Germany. Our results highlight the importance of combined measures, such as vaccination campaigns and targeted contact reductions to achieve temporary epidemic control.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Germany’s fourth COVID-19 wave was mainly driven by the unvaccinated</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-germany/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-germany/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Enhancing global preparedness during an ongoing pandemic from partial and noisy data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is testing at home sufficient? Self tests and official statistics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/datenspende_blog_incidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/datenspende_blog_incidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Preprint Out: Modeling the impact of the Omicron infection wave in Germany</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2021, the first case of SARS-CoV-2 “variant of concern” (VOC) B.1.1.529 (“Omicron”) was reported in Germany, alongside global reports of reduced vaccine efficacy against infections with this variant. The potential threat posed by the rapid spread of this variant in Germany remained, at the time, elusive.
We developed a variant-dependent population-averaged susceptible-exposed-infected-recovered (SEIR) infectious disease model. The model was calibrated on the observed fixation dynamics of the Omicron variant in December 2021, and allowed us to estimate potential courses of upcoming infection waves in Germany, focusing on the corresponding burden on intensive care units (ICUs) and the efficacy of contact reduction strategies. A maximum median incidence of approximately 300 000 (50% PI in 1000: [181,454], 95% PI in 1000: [55,804]) reported cases per day was expected with the median peak occurring in the mid of February 2022, reaching a cumulative Omicron case count of 16.5 million (50% PI in mio: [11.4, 21.3], 95% PI in mio: [4.1, 27.9]) until Apr 1, 2022. These figures were in line with the actual Omicron waves that were subsequently observed in Germany with respective peaks occurring in mid February (peak: 191k daily new cases) and mid March (peak: 230k daily new cases), cumulatively infecting 14.8 million individuals during the study period. The model peak incidence was observed to be highly sensitive to variations in the assumed generation time and decreased with shorter generation time. Low contact reductions were expected to lead to containment. Early, strict, and short contact reductions could have led to a strong “rebound” effect with high incidences after the end of the respective non-pharmaceutical interventions. Higher vaccine uptake would have led to a lower outbreak size. To ensure that ICU occupancy remained below maximum capacity, a relative risk of requiring ICU care of 10%–20% was necessary (after infection with Omicron vs. infection with Delta).
We expected a large cumulative number of infections with the VOC Omicron in Germany with ICU occupancy likely remaining below capacity nevertheless, even without additional non-pharmaceutical interventions. Our estimates were in line with the retrospectively observed waves. The results presented here informed legislation in Germany. The methodology developed in this study might be used to estimate the impact of future waves of COVID-19 or other infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint: Estimating the distribution of COVID-19-susceptible, -recovered, and -vaccinated individuals in Germany up to April 2022</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/sero_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/sero_preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.04.19.22274030v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.04.19.22274030v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint: Evidence for positive long- and short-term effects of vaccinations against COVID-19 in wearable sensor metrics -- Insights from the German Corona Data Donation Project</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/long_covid_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/long_covid_preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we use physiological data collected in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.de/science/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;German Data Donation Project (Datenspende)&lt;/a&gt; to investigate the differential impact of vaccination on the effect that a COVID-19 infection has on &lt;strong&gt;resting heart rate&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;physical activity&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sleep&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02846&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02846&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abschätzung der Infektionswelle durch die SARS-CoV-2 VOC Omikron</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-omicron/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-omicron/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Die Pandemie wird durch fehlenden Impfschutz getrieben: Was ist zu tun?</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-pandemie/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-pandemie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;wichtig&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wichtig:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die hier beschriebenen wissenschaftlichen Ergebnisse beziehen sich auf die &lt;strong&gt;B.1.617.2&lt;/strong&gt; SARS-CoV-2 Variante (&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Delta&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;) und das Infektionsgeschehen Mitte November in Deutschland. Die Ergebnisse spiegeln nicht die Situation der Omicron-Welle (SARS-CoV-2-Variante &lt;strong&gt;B.1.1.529&lt;/strong&gt;) Anfang 2022 wieder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impfungen gehören du den wirksamsten Mitteln der Pandemiebekämpfung. Trotzdem sind die Impfraten im &lt;a href=&#34;https://ourworldindata.org/covid-vaccinations?country=OWID_WRL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;deutschsprachigen Europa&lt;/a&gt; aktuell viel zu niedrig für eine effektive Eindämmung des Virus. In Deutschland waren am 22.11.2021 68% doppelt geimpft, obwohl das &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjH84v28rD0AhWJzKQKHfsXCJUQFnoECAUQAQ&amp;amp;url=https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/Infekt/EpidBull/Archiv/2021/27/Art_01.html&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0G9DqJ7ijemGlZYRwXrZbW&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RKI&lt;/a&gt; bereits im Juli 2021 empfahl, 85% der 12-59-Jährigen und 90% der Über-60-Jährigen zu impfen. Ähnlich schlecht sieht es in Österreich (65% vollständig geimpft) und der Schweiz (66%) aus. Auffrischungsimpfungen (Booster) zur Erhöhung der Impfeffektivität sind seit November in Deutschland &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/Kommissionen/STIKO/Empfehlungen/PM_2021-11-18.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;empfohlen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neue Berechnungen auf der Basis eines mathematischen Ansteckungsmodells &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; zeigen, dass eine effektive Erhöhung der Impfquote jedoch dringend notwendig ist: bei 8 bis 9 von 10 Ansteckungen mit COVID-19 ist mindestens eine ungeimpfte Person beteiligt. Das folgende Beispiel illustriert, dass aktuell der Großteil der Neuinfektionen durch fehlenden Impfschutz verursacht wird, obwohl ungeimpfte Personen nur ca. 32% der Bevölkerung ausmachen.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-abb1&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb1_hue3d634736fd43df10aac553ccb3f4083_157779_ccdfe103bc690c00c7c2fc9987d18c85.jpeg 400w,
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb1_hue3d634736fd43df10aac553ccb3f4083_157779_ad3a9845a07c9004e239652e5336d0a3.jpeg 760w,
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb1_hue3d634736fd43df10aac553ccb3f4083_157779_1200x1200_fit_q75_lanczos.jpeg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb1_hue3d634736fd43df10aac553ccb3f4083_157779_ccdfe103bc690c00c7c2fc9987d18c85.jpeg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Abbildung zeigt, wie ungeimpfte und geimpfte Personen anteilig an der Verbreitung von COVID-19 beteiligt sind (laut Modellschätzungen). Man stelle sich eine Gruppe von Infizierten vor. Angenommen, diese Gruppe hat 100 Ansteckungen verursacht. In der oberen Grafik (A) wird eine Impfeffektivität von 72% bei Erwachsenen und 92% bei Kindern und
Jugendlichen angenommen. Dann sehen die 100 Ansteckungen folgendermaßen aus: 51
von den 100 Angesteckten sind Ungeimpfte, die von anderen Ungeimpften infiziert wurden. 25 sind Geimpfte, die von Ungeimpften infiziert wurden. Es wurden also 76 Personen von Ungeimpften angesteckt. Der Anteil der Leute, der durch Geimpfte angesteckt wird, ist erheblich kleiner: 15 Angesteckte sind Ungeimpfte, die von Geimpften angesteckt wurden und 9 sind Geimpfte, die von Geimpften angesteckt wurden. Es wurden also lediglich 24 Personen von Geimpften angesteckt. 91 von 100 Ansteckungen entstehen mit Beteiligung mindestens einer Person ohne Impfschutz.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-abb2&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb2_hucbf4ebb6e9f66eebdac69406ef95838f_156632_808930b7bcafa70c4f5a142c5d509e80.jpeg 400w,
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb2_hucbf4ebb6e9f66eebdac69406ef95838f_156632_76d6c27b8cacea6619e2388996f3b37f.jpeg 760w,
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb2_hucbf4ebb6e9f66eebdac69406ef95838f_156632_1200x1200_fit_q75_lanczos.jpeg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb2_hucbf4ebb6e9f66eebdac69406ef95838f_156632_808930b7bcafa70c4f5a142c5d509e80.jpeg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Um zu verstehen, ob neue Ansteckungen auch durch fehlenden Impfschutz getrieben werden, wenn die Impfung nur eine geringe Effektivität hat, wurde in einem zweiten Beispiel eine geringere Impfeffektivität angenommen &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In der unteren Grafik wird eine Impfeffektivität von 50% bei über 60ig-Jährigen, 60% bei Erwachsenen bis 59 Jahren und 60% bei Kindern und Jugendlichen bis 17 Jahren angenommen. Dann sehen die 100 Infektionen folgendermaßen aus: 38 von den 100 Angesteckten sind Ungeimpfte, die von anderen Ungeimpften infiziert wurden. 29 sind Geimpfte, die von Ungeimpften infiziert wurden. Es wurden also 67 Personen von Ungeimpften angesteckt. Der Anteil der Leute, der durch Geimpfte angesteckt wird, ist erheblich kleiner: 17 Angesteckte sind Ungeimpfte, die von Geimpften angesteckt wurden und 16 sind Geimpfte, die von Geimpften angesteckt wurden. Es wurden also lediglich 33 Neuinfizierte von Geimpften angesteckt. 84 von 100 Ansteckungen entstehen mit Beteiligung mindestens einer Person ohne Impfschutz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;daraus-ergibt-sich&#34;&gt;Daraus ergibt sich:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An 8 bis 9 von 10 Ansteckungen sind Personen ohne Impfschutz beteiligt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Je effektiver der Impfschutz, desto weniger Ansteckungen werden durch geimpfte Personen verursacht.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Die Dynamik der Pandemie wird aktuell also stark durch fehlenden oder nachlassenden, weniger effektiven Impfschutz getrieben.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;daher-empfiehlt-sich&#34;&gt;Daher empfiehlt sich:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impfquote effektiv erhöhen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effektivität des Impfschutzes erhöhen, z.B. durch Boostern.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kontakte reduzieren, v.a. zwischen ungeimpften Personen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ohne zusätzliche Maßnahmen ist keine baldige Besserung der Impfquote zu erwarten, da die Zuwachsrate der Impfkampagne seit Juni 2021 &lt;a href=&#34;http://impfdashboard.de/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;stagniert&lt;/a&gt;. Für zusätzliche Maßnahmen zur Steigerung der Impfquote besteht die Herausforderung, dass ein Großteil der ungeimpften Personen schwer erreichbar ist - z.B. laut der &lt;a href=&#34;https://projekte.uni-erfurt.de/cosmo2020/web/summary/56/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;COSMO-Studie&lt;/a&gt; sind 30% der Ungeimpften zögerlich, 54% sagen, sie wollen sich auf keinen Fall impfen lassen (Stand November 2021). Vor- und Nachteile eine Impfpflicht sollten &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/pmx3w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;diskutiert werden&lt;/a&gt;. Maßnahmen, die schnell die Kontakte reduzieren, sollten zum Brechen der 4. Welle implementiert werden, da selbst ein schneller Anstieg der Impfrate erst mittelfristig weitere Wellen verhindern, nicht aber die aktuelle Welle brechen kann.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kontakt:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bfmaier@physik.hu-berlin.de&#34;&gt;bfmaier@physik.hu-berlin.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preprint:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/publication/maier-2021-germany/maier-2021-germany.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Germany’s current COVID-19 crisis is mainly driven by the unvaccinated&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das theoretische Framework hinter diesen Berechnungen heisst Contribution Matrix. Die Berechnungen sind detailliert hier beschrieben: &lt;a href=&#34;https://rocs.hu-berlin.de/publication/maier-2021-germany/maier-2021-germany.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://rocs.hu-berlin.de/publication/maier-2021- germany/maier-2021-germany.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beide Szenarien gehen von folgenden aktuellen Impfraten pro Altersgruppe aus: 0-11 = 0%, 12-17 = 40%, 18-59 = 72%, 60+ = 85%. Über die tatsächliche Impfeffektivität besteht wissenschaftliche Unsicherheit. Daher werden zwei verschiedene Szenarien angenommen. In Szenario A wird eine hohe Impfeffektivität von 92% bei Kindern und 72% bei Erwachsenen angenommen. Dies entspricht den Effektivitäten der Periode Oktober 2021 für symptomatisches COVID-19 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/InfAZ/N/Neuartiges_Coronavirus/Situationsberichte/Gesamt.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RKI Situationsbericht vom 11.11.2021&lt;/a&gt;). Im Modell werden jedoch Impfeffektivitäten gegen Infektion angenommen, die üblicherweise geringer sind als gegen symptomatisches COVID-19. Diese Effektivitätsschätzung ist daher eine optimistische Schätzung und dient dies als mögliche Obergrenze. Die niedrigeren Impfeffktivitäten gegen Infektion (Szenario B) sind in Übereinstimmung mit Daten aus Großbritannien gewählt (50% bei über 60ig-Jährigen, 60% bei Erwachsenen bis 59 Jahren und 60% bei Kindern und Jugendlichen bis 17 Jahren). In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abm0620&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Großbritannien&lt;/a&gt; wurde vorwiegend mit AstraZeneca geimpft. Dieser Impfstoff gilt in der Literatur als weniger effektiv. Daher dienen diese Werte im Modell als Schätzung für niedrige Impfeffektivität gegen Infektion. Die Ansteckungs-Zahlen beschreiben die geschätzten Anteile der Infektionswege an der totalen effektiven Reproduktionszahl (Reff). Zum Zeitpunkt dieser Berechnungen lag R etwa bei &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/robert-koch-institut/SARS-CoV-2-Nowcasting_und_-R-Schaetzung/blob/main/Nowcast_R_aktuell.csv&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;1,2&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding disease outbreak locations from human mobility data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2021-finding/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2021-finding/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out: Finding disease outbreak locations from human mobility data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/outbreak_detection/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/outbreak_detection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we investigated how much information on individual mobility patterns is required
to reconstruct the origin of an outbreak from spatially distributed cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out: not so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://epjdatascience.springeropen.com/articles/10.1140/epjds/s13688-021-00306-6#citeas&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding the origin location of an infectious disease outbreak quickly is crucial in
mitigating its further dissemination. Current methods to identify outbreak locations
early on rely on interviewing affected individuals and correlating their movements,
which is a manual, time-consuming, and error-prone process. Other methods such as
contact tracing, genomic sequencing or theoretical models of epidemic spread offer
help, but they are not applicable at the onset of an outbreak as they require highly
processed information or established transmission chains. Digital data sources such as
mobile phones offer new ways to find outbreak sources in an automated way. Here,
we propose a novel method to determine outbreak origins from geolocated
movement data of individuals affected by the outbreak. Our algorithm scans
movement trajectories for shared locations and identifies the outbreak origin as the
most dominant among them. We test the method using various empirical and
synthetic datasets, and demonstrate that it is able to single out the true outbreak
location with high accuracy, requiring only data of N = 4 individuals. The method can
be applied to scenarios with multiple outbreak locations, and is even able to estimate
the number of outbreak sources if unknown, while being robust to noise. Our
method is the first to offer a reliable, accurate out-of-the-box approach to identify
outbreak locations in the initial phase of an outbreak. It can be easily and quickly
applied in a crisis situation, improving on previous manual approaches. The method is
not only applicable in the context of disease outbreaks, but can be used to find
shared locations in movement data in other contexts as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Monitor: Contact patterns during the Pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/contact_monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/contact_monitor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to mobility, we now show the average contacts in the population over time—with equally important insights into the course of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mobility of people gives us an important overview of the pandemic, but it is actually the contacts between people that are instrumental in the infection dynamics: Transmissions occur when people meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the new &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/contact-index/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;contact monitor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we make these contacts visible. The monitor shows the average number of contacts that a person in Germany had on a given day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can clearly see how strongly contacts have decreased in March 2020, and how they are still at a low level more than a year after the start of the pandemic. Also visible are the different phases of the pandemic and reactions to it with lockdowns, relaxations, holidays and vacations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of contacts is calculated from GPS mobile phone data and provided to us as an anonymous, aggregated statistic - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org/data-info/contacts/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;more on the methodology here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will continue to analyze contact dynamics and investigate what conclusions can be drawn about infection dynamics. For example, in the study &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/118/31/e2026731118&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ruediger et al.&lt;/a&gt;, contacts were shown to be related to the reproductive number R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Digital contact tracing contributes little to COVID-19 outbreak containment</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/tracing_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/tracing_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our preprint &amp;ldquo;Digital contact tracing contributes little to COVID-19 outbreak containment&amp;rdquo; is out and available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As digital contact tracing apps raised the hope that they may be efficient enough to contain outbreaks
without falling back to harsher NPIs, we analyzed its success. Relying on empirical results, we find
an expected outbreak size reduction on the order of a few percent at best. While the intervention
may aid the manual tracing process, we argue that countries should concentrate on other means to contain
COVID-19 outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital contact tracing applications have been introduced in many countries to aid in the containment of
COVID-19 outbreaks. Initially, enthusiasm was high regarding their implementation as a non-pharmaceutical
intervention (NPI). Yet, no country was able to prevent larger outbreaks without falling back to harsher NPIs,
and the total effect of digital contact tracing remains elusive. Based on the results of empirical studies and
modeling efforts, we show that digital contact tracing apps might have prevented cases on the order of single-digit
percentages up until now, at best. We show that this poor impact can be attributed to a combination of low
participation rates, a non-flexible reliance on symptom-based testing, low engagement of participants, and
delays between testing and test result upload. We find that contact tracing does not change the epidemic
threshold and exclusively prevents more cases during the supercritical phase of an epidemic, making it unfit
as a tool to prevent outbreaks. Locally clustered contact structures may increase the intervention’s efficacy,
but only if the number of contacts per individual is homogeneously distributed, a condition usually not found in
contact networks.  Our results suggest that policy makers cannot rely on digital contact tracing to contain
outbreaks of COVID-19 or similar diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dirk  @ Jung &amp; Naiv - Folge 503</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_jung_und_naiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_jung_und_naiv/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact Index Monitor</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/contactindex-monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/contactindex-monitor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;contact-index-monitor&#34;&gt;Contact Index Monitor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;width: 100%; height: 450px; border: 1px solid #ddd; margin: 20px 0;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe 
    src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/viz/contactindex-monitor/&#34; 
    width=&#34;100%&#34; 
    height=&#34;100%&#34; 
    frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
    style=&#34;border: none;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How a pandemic develops depends on many factors: the biology of the pathogen, its susceptibility to external influences such as humidity and temperature, but most of all it is determined by contacts between individuals: transmissions occur primarily when people have contact with each other. The number of contacts thus gives us an insight into the course of the pandemic. Fewer contacts make it more difficult for the pathogen to spread through the population, whereas more contacts promote rapid spread. In the Contacts Monitor, we show the number of contacts and its variation in Germany over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;width: 100%; height: 1000px; border: 1px solid #ddd; margin: 20px 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe 
    src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/viz/contactindex-monitor/states.html&#34; 
    width=&#34;100%&#34; 
    height=&#34;100%&#34; 
    frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
    scrolling=&#34;no&#34;
    style=&#34;border: none; overflow: hidden;
    onload=&#34;this.contentDocument.body.style.overflow=&#39;hidden&#39;;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-potential/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-potential/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are happy that our preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2102.13600.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is out and available on &lt;em&gt;arxiv.org&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a very constructive and effective collaborative effort, lead by our &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/author/dr.-benjamin-f.-maier/&#34;&gt;Ben Maier&lt;/a&gt;, who did all the heavy lifting, and valuable contributions by the teams of Cornelia Betsch, Michael Meyer-Hermann and by Karl Lauterbach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell we evaluate and compare different vaccination strageties of COVID-19 mRNA-vaccines in high-risk groups in Germany and show that a flexible scheduling of the second vaccine dose can potentially be the way to go. If you are interested in the details, have a look at the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vaccination against COVID-19 with the recently approved mRNA vaccines BNT162b2 (BioNTech/Pfizer) and mRNA-1273 (Moderna) is currently underway in a large number of countries. However, high incidence rates and rapidly spreading SARS-CoV-2 variants are concerning. In combination with acute supply deficits in Europe in early 2021, the question arises of whether stretching the vaccine, for instance by delaying the second dose, can make a significant contribution to preventing deaths, despite associated risks such as lower vaccine efficacy, the potential emergence of escape mutants, enhancement, waning immunity, reduced social acceptance of off-label vaccination, and liability shifts. A quantitative epidemiological assessment of risks and benefits of non-standard vaccination protocols remains elusive. To clarify the situation and to provide a quantitative epidemiological foundation we develop a stochastic epidemiological model that integrates specific vaccine rollout protocols into a risk-group structured infectious disease dynamical model. Using the situation and conditions in Germany as a reference system, we show that delaying the second vaccine dose is expected to prevent deaths in the four to five digit range, should the incidence resurge. We show that this considerable public health benefit relies on the fact that both mRNA vaccines provide substantial protection against severe COVID-19 and death beginning 12 to 14 days after the first dose. The benefits of protocol change are attenuated should vaccine compliance decrease substantially. To quantify the impact of protocol change on vaccination adherence we performed a large-scale online survey. We find that, in Germany, changing vaccination protocols may lead to small reductions in vaccination intention. In sum, we therefore expect the benefits of a strategy change to remain substantial and stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dirk Brockmann macht Schule</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_9th_grade/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dirk_9th_grade/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alles, was das Unterwegssein bremst, ist jetzt sinnvoll</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/press/zeitonline_2021_01_21/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/press/zeitonline_2021_01_21/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wir müssen an allen Ecken ganz massiv Kontakte reduzieren</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/press/rbb24_2021_01_15/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/press/rbb24_2021_01_15/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Corona Datenspende App</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/datenspende/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/datenspende/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pressekonferenz des RKI</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/press/youtube_2021_01_14/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/press/youtube_2021_01_14/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 lockdown induces disease-mitigating structural changes in mobility networks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2020-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2020-covid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>German COVID-19 Snapshot Monitoring (COSMO)-Welle 11 (12.05.2020)</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/betsch-2020-kosmo-welle11/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/betsch-2020-kosmo-welle11/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coronavirus-Pandemie--Die Krise nachhaltig überwinden</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/brockmann-2020-coronavirus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/brockmann-2020-coronavirus/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>German COVID-19 Snapshot Monitoring (COSMO)-Welle 9 (28.04.2020)</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/betsch-2020-kosmo-welle9/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/betsch-2020-kosmo-welle9/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effective containment explains subexponential growth in recent confirmed COVID-19 cases in China</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2020-effective/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2020-effective/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
