<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Large language models | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/large-language-models/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/large-language-models/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Large language models</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>Large language models</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/large-language-models/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint on decision-making and large language models</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/preprint-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/preprint-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our colleague &lt;strong&gt;Kamil Fulawka&lt;/strong&gt; is the first author of a new preprint investigating how large language models (LLMs) can be used to understand the psychology of risky choice. Together with &lt;strong&gt;Ralph Hertwig&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Dirk Wulff&lt;/strong&gt;, he introduces a scalable approach to analyze participants’ free-text explanations of their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study shows that LLMs can accurately identify the reasons people give for their lottery choices in more than &lt;strong&gt;92% of cases&lt;/strong&gt;. These verbal reports reveal systematic patterns: people’s reasoning depends strongly on the &lt;strong&gt;structure of the choice problem&lt;/strong&gt; rather than being fixed across individuals. Models based on these reason profiles also achieve &lt;strong&gt;higher predictive accuracy than prospect theory&lt;/strong&gt;, one of the most established frameworks in decision science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By demonstrating the &lt;strong&gt;scientific value of verbal data&lt;/strong&gt;, the work opens new avenues for developing context-aware models of human decision-making. We are proud of Kamil’s contribution to this important line of research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/yuzmw_v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the preprint here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
