<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Clonal interference | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/clonal-interference/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/clonal-interference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Clonal interference</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>Clonal interference</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/clonal-interference/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Network Structure Shapes Evolutionary Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/network_structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/network_structure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our colleague &lt;strong&gt;Adrian Zachariae&lt;/strong&gt; has published a new preprint on how network structure shapes evolutionary dynamics in asexual populations. The study examines clonal interference the competition between beneficial mutations, and demonstrates that this process is strongly influenced by the topology of the underlying network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through computational modelling and a novel analytical approach inspired by epidemic research, Adrian and his co-authors show how mutation rates and network geometry interact to generate distinct evolutionary regimes. These regimes determine where high-fitness strains emerge and how they spread across the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings offer new perspectives on how spatial heterogeneity affects adaptation, with relevance for understanding pathogen evolution, conservation biology, and other complex systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.10.20.683208v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the preprint on bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origins of the Fittest: Clonal Interference in Heterogeneous Networks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/origins-of-the-fittest-2026/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/origins-of-the-fittest-2026/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clonal Interference in Heterogeneous Networks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/clonal_interference/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/clonal_interference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our research group explores the intricate relationship between complex environmental structures and evolutionary processes, focusing on clonal interference in asexual populations. We aim to understand how organisms adapt in heterogeneous, network-like environments that closely resemble real-world scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clonal interference (CI) occurs in asexual populations when multiple beneficial mutations arise and compete, unable to combine through recombination. While CI has been studied in well-mixed or simple spatial structures, its behavior in complex, heterogeneous environments remains largely unexplored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;optional_cool.gif&#34; alt=&#34;cool gif&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key Research Aims:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding CI in Highly Heterogeneous Environments: We investigate how diverse network topologies influence clonal interference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying Key Structural Components: We aim to pinpoint specific elements of network structures that significantly impact adaptive processes, understanding which features promote faster adaptation and which areas are likely sources of adaptive mutations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shaping and Controlling Adaptive Evolution: By understanding how network structures influence evolution, we seek to develop strategies for potentially guiding adaptive processes in complex environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing Analytical Tools: We&amp;rsquo;re working to create and refine mathematical and computational tools that effectively model and predict evolutionary dynamics in intricate systems, bridging network theory, evolutionary biology, and complex systems science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The insights gained from our research have potential applications across a wide range of fields. In epidemiology, our understanding of how pathogens evolve in structured host populations could form more effective disease management strategies. Conservation biologists might use our findings to guide habitat management practices, supporting species adaptation and resilience in fragmented environments. Our work could also lead to improved bioprocess designs by accounting for how environmental structure affects microbial evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond these direct applications, the principles we uncover might have broader, more speculative implications. For instance, our approaches to mutation spread in biological networks could provide insights into how content goes viral on social media platforms with diverse user structures. The competition between genetic strains in our research might elucidate how ideas, innovations and cultural practices propagate through social and professional networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we continue to explore the intricate interplay between network complexity and evolutionary dynamics, we&amp;rsquo;re not merely advancing theoretical knowledge. We&amp;rsquo;re developing a deeper, more nuanced understanding of how adaptation occurs in complex systems. This research has the potential to open new avenues for managing and harnessing evolutionary processes in various fields, spanning from biology to the social sciences. By bridging the gap between network theory and evolutionary biology, we&amp;rsquo;re paving the way for a more comprehensive understanding of how information – be it genetic, cultural, or technological – spreads and competes in our interconnected world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
