<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Information Environment | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/information-environment/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/information-environment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Information Environment</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>Information Environment</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/information-environment/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New multi-author preprint about who should govern online environments</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/choice_architects/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/choice_architects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this multi-author paper, spearheaded by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mpib-berlin.mpg.de/person/friederike-stock/419405&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Friederike Stock&lt;/a&gt;, and as part of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://jrp.pscholars.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Junior Researcher Program&lt;/a&gt; with young researchers from 26 different countries and the project was supervised by Philipp Lorenz-Spreen. Little is known about who users themselves think should control their online environments, and under what circumstances. In our preregistered study, participants across 26 countries (N = 11,686) decided between combinations of three possible choice architects—governments, platforms, and individuals—and three objectives—societal, commercial, and personal—in seven real-world contexts. Across all countries, people strongly prefer to set their own rules for their online choice architectures. Find the full preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/preprints/osf/haqu9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Study Reveals Who’s Most Vulnerable to Misinformation—and why</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/misinformation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/misinformation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our junior research group leader Philipp Lorenz-Spreen, whose work focuses on the digital information environment and among other things on misinformation, has co-authored a comprehensive meta-analysis of over 256,000 decisions from thousands of participants that sheds light on who is most susceptible to misinformation and the factors behind it. Their research reveals that susceptibility depends less on formal education and more on individual and contextual factors, such as age, analytical thinking, and political alignment. Older adults and those with strong analytical skills tend to discern truth from falsehood better, though they are also more skeptical, which means they classify more news as false overall. A tendency called “true news bias” emerges when people encounter news aligning with their political beliefs or previously seen content, making them more prone to believe information without scrutiny. These findings offer valuable insights for his further studies of the spreading dynamics of misinformation and the development of interventions that help people to navigate the information environment of the internet. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2409329121&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read in full here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
