<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Philipp Lorenz-Spreen | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/philipp/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/authors/philipp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Philipp Lorenz-Spreen</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/authors/philipp/avatar_hu86389fcb32ce01ca9990d65286572d78_1429256_270x270_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Philipp Lorenz-Spreen</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/philipp/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Opportunities and Challenges of the EU&#39;s Digital Services Act</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillip-2025-digital-service-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillip-2025-digital-service-act/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Paper: Understanding Participation Inequality in Online Political Discussions</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/inequality_online_political_discussions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/inequality_online_political_discussions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A new paper supervised by Philipp Lorenz-Spreen was published yesterday. It addresses a well known problem in digital public spaces. Online debates are often distorted because a loud and sometimes politically extreme minority dominates the conversation while most users remain silent. The study asks how this pattern can change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team ran a collective field experiment on Reddit. Over four weeks, 520 participants discussed 20 political issues in six private communities. The study tested how monetary incentives and moderation prompts shape participation and discourse quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings are clear: Incentives reduced participation inequality, while reminders to “stay civil” unexpectedly increased toxicity. Highly active users posted more when they perceived the environment as polarized. Silent users, in contrast, joined the conversation when discussions felt respectful and constructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper shows how platform design and perceived discussion climate influence who speaks up and how positive incentives can help make online discourse more inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the paper: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.ady8022&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.ady8022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling Participation in Online Political Discussions with a Collective Field Experiment</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2025_reddit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2025_reddit/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What a blast! Philipp Lorenz-Spreen at re:publica 2025</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/republica-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/republica-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, our colleague Philipp Lorenz-Spreen took the stage at &lt;strong&gt;re:publica 2025&lt;/strong&gt; to address one of the most pressing questions of our digital era:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Gesellschaftliche Kipppunkte: Die Spirale aus Aufmerksamkeit und Plattformmacht und wie wir da noch rauskommen”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;em&gt;“Societal Tipping Points: The Spiral of Attention and Platform Power – and How We Might Escape It”&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his talk, he explored how notifications, newsfeeds, and social platforms constantly demand our attention – and how this attention has become a source of power with far-reaching political consequences. Moving from everyday habits to systemic impacts, he examined how platform dynamics influence democratic discourse and what needs to change for us to regain agency and foster a healthier public debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His session sparked thoughtful discussions around the architecture of digital platforms, the challenges of measurements in social sciences, and the urgent need for alternative models that empower users rather than exploit their attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re proud to see our research contributing to this important conversation. Thank you to the re:publica community for the energy, engagement, and inspiration!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📺 &lt;strong&gt;Full talk available online&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/7j4QIayjAaY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Watch here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Methods for Computational Social Sciences</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/teaching/methods_css/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/teaching/methods_css/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Opal: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bildungsportal.sachsen.de/opal/auth/RepositoryEntry/48847978502/CourseNode/1743388566773105003/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time (Lecture) Mondays, 3. DS and 5. DS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location APB/E001&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Department Computer Science&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modules INF-BAS3 (Software- und Web-Engineering)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language English&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assessment oral exam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lecture will introduce you to social science research questions and findings, while the exercise will give you the practical skills to answer social questions yourself using computational tools. The first part focuses on basic techniques of text analysis. We will learn how to collect text data from sources such as newspapers, parliamentary minutes or social media, and how to pre-process it for natural language processing (NLP), such as sentiment analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will then move on to analyzing the structural factors of online data, from time series to networks and their dynamics. We will also explore how to collect such data from social media and how to conduct online field experiments. We will then have the tools to move on to applied research questions, covering topics such as political polarization, misinformation, public health and human mobility. We will learn what conclusions can and cannot be drawn from these descriptions. Finally, we will go beyond description and learn about causality, simulation models of social systems that allow mechanistic understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last part of the course will focus on NLP again, this time with a focus on deep learning methods such as Large Language Models (LLMs). We will use transformer models to identify complex patterns in the communication of German parties on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, this course will provide a toolbox for describing different types of social systems with a focus on textual data, as well as a family of modelling approaches that can go beyond individual-level statistics to describe collective processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;schedule&#34;&gt;Schedule:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 1 What is Computational Social Science?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 2 Data, types, sources and preparation in R/Python&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 3 Collecting text data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 4 Identifying sentiment and clusters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 5 Time series analysis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 6 Regressions and statistical modeling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 7 Network science 1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 8 Network science 2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 9 Causal inference in observational data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Break June 8 - 15&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 10 Agent-based-models&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 11 Topic Modeling with Transformers 1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 12 Topic Modeling with Transformers 2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 13 LLMs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Week 14 Final session, feedback, Q&amp;amp;A, Discussion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bibliography&#34;&gt;Bibliography:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Llaudet, E., &amp;amp; Imai, K. (2022). Data analysis for social science: A friendly and practical introduction. Princeton University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albert-László Barabási (2015). Network Science. Cambridge University Press (also here: networksciencebook.com)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cunningham, S. (2021). Causal inference: The mixtape. Yale university press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lazer, D., Pentland, A., Adamic, L., Aral, S., Barabási, A. L., Brewer, D., &amp;hellip; &amp;amp; Van Alstyne, M. (2009). Computational social science. Science, 323(5915), 721-723.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flache, A., Mäs, M., Feliciani, T., Chattoe-Brown, E., Deffuant, G., Huet, S., &amp;amp; Lorenz, J. (2017). Models of social influence: Towards the next frontiers. Jasss-The journal of artificial societies and social simulation, 20(4), 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lorenz-Spreen, P., Oswald, L., Lewandowsky, S., &amp;amp; Hertwig, R. (2023). A systematic review of worldwide causal and correlational evidence on digital media and democracy. Nature human behaviour, 7(1), 74-101.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time assessment of motives for sharing and creating content among highly active Twitter users</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillip-2024-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillip-2024-twitter/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toolbox of individual-level interventions against online misinformation</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2024-toolbox/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2024-toolbox/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Susceptibility to Online Misinformation: A Systematic Meta-Analysis of Demographic and Psychological Factors</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2024-susceptibility/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2024-susceptibility/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Evolution of Online News Headlines</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2024-evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2024-evolution/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Directing smartphone use through the self-nudge app one sec</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2023-smartphone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2023-smartphone/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A systematic review of worldwide causal and correlational evidence on digital media and democracy</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2022-systematic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2022-systematic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boosting people’s ability to detect microtargeted advertising</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2021-boosting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2021-boosting/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How behavioural sciences can promote truth, autonomy and democratic discourse online</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2020-behavioural/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2020-behavioural/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling echo chambers and polarization dynamics in social networks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2020-echo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2020-echo/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating dynamics of collective attention</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2019-accelerating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2019-accelerating/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
