<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>social media | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/social-media/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/social-media/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>social media</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>social media</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/social-media/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New replication study examines the influence of digital media on democracy</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/replication/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/replication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;© [AI] ChatGPT / MPG adapted from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mpg.de/24519906/digital-media-a-threat-to-democracy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research team systematically replicated the methodology of the original study and used an updated dataset with studies up to March 2024. The results confirm the findings of the original study: Digital media have many problematic effects on democratic processes, in addition to positive ones. On the one hand, they promote political participation and facilitate access to information. On the other hand, they increase polarization, mistrust in institutions, and populist movements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent research paper by the Institute for Replication (I4R) analyzes and reviews the results of the 2023 study, ‘A Systematic Review of Worldwide Causal and Correlational Evidence on Digital Media and Democracy,’ by Lorenz-Spreen et al. The replication study, conducted by researchers from Tongji University, the University of Cambridge, and Duke University, confirms the original findings on the relationships between digital media and democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The replication study supports our findings, and the worrying trends continue,” explains Philipp Lorenz-Spreen, research group leader for Computational Social Science at TU Dresden and research scientist at the Max Planck Institute for Human Development (MPIB) in Berlin. He and Lisa Oswald – both working at the Center for Adaptive Rationality – led the 2023 study. Postdoctoral researcher Lisa Oswald underscores the significance of these findings. “The correlative evidence is mounting that digital media can negatively influence political processes – we see increased polarization, rising mistrust in democratic institutions and media, and a proliferation of misinformation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replication study: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ideas.repec.org/p/zbw/i4rdps/206.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://ideas.repec.org/p/zbw/i4rdps/206.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Original study: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-022-01460-1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-022-01460-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Alice Weidel and the AfD benefit from Musk&#39;s attention on X?</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/x-election/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/x-election/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Has Elon Musk manipulated X to give the AfD more reach? He has made it clear in posts, articles and election events that he is a fan - and at the same time, Alice Weidel’s reach on X has increased significantly. Could these developments be linked? This blog post describes a data analysis in which we take a closer look at which accounts have received how much reach and whether Musk’s influence can be determined. Where does the sudden increase in Weidel’s reach on X come from?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: This work has not yet been peer reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, there has been a lot of fuss about Elon Musk’s possible influence in favour of the AfD. First, on 20 December, he wrote on his platform X (formerly Twitter) that only the AfD can save Germany. On 28 December, Die Welt published a guest article by Musk in which he expressed the same position. Finally, on 9 January, he held a public conversation on X with the AfD candidate Alice Weidel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As already reported in one place or another, Weidel gained a lot of reach on X. The German parliamentary administration then announced that it would investigate whether Musk is influencing the election campaign. At the same time, the EU Commission is demanding insight into possible changes to X’s recommendation algorithms. This article analyses the possible impact of Musk’s activities on the reach of the AfD and Weidel in particular on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do Community Notes have a party preference?</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/community_notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/community_notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community notes are supposed to curb disinformation on X - but they themselves follow political patterns. A new data analysis shows that Green Party posts are particularly criticised, but their notes are hardly considered helpful. At the same time, there is no clear political trend in the notes that are actually published. Why is this the case? The article analyses patterns in the distribution and rating of the notes and sheds light on the dynamics that can be derived from the data.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: This work has not yet been peer reviewed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;community-notes-instead-of-fact-checks&#34;&gt;Community Notes instead of Fact-checks?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the year, &lt;a href=&#34;https://about.fb.com/news/2025/01/meta-more-speech-fewer-mistakes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt; Meta&amp;rsquo;s CEO Mark Zuckerberg announced &lt;/a&gt; that the company was ending its collaboration with independent fact-checkers replacing them with X-style Community Notes (Notes for short). Zuckerberg claimed that fact-checking limited free speech. However, &lt;a href=&#34;https://netzpolitik.org/2025/zuckerbergs-kehrtwende-meta-goes-maga/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;it seems more likely&lt;/a&gt; that this is a concession to Trump and the Republican Party, who accuse fact-checkers of being politically motivated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accusation that fact-checking is biased in favour of the left or liberal camp is not new and is also made in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nzz.ch/meinung/faktenchecks-zuckerberg-musk-trump-medien-aktivismus-ard-faktenfinder-russland-nordstream-propaganda-fake-news-ld.1867044&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;German-speaking countries&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, fact-checking, like any other journalistic genre, is not free of errors and distortions. However, it is often overlooked that disinformation is frequently associated with right-wing and populist attitudes (Lasser et al. 2022, Törnberg and Chueri 2025). If fact-checks tend to scrutinise right-wing actors, this does not necessarily reveal a bias, but could also reflect an actual asymmetry (Mosleh et al. 2024). For example, a recent study shows that helpful Notes are also more likely to be found in posts from the Republicans (Renault et al. 2025).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post presents the results of a data analysis of German-language Notes that were rated as helpful or unhelpful at least 20 times and published between January 2024 and January 2025 inclusive. As Notes will also be launched on Facebook and Instagram in the future (initially only in the US), it is worth asking whether there is a focus on parties from a particular ideological spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-do-community-notes-work-on-x&#34;&gt;How do Community Notes work on X?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes are found as comments on posts and are intended to point out their shortcomings. The Notes for this data analysis show posts as incorrect or unverified (Fig. 1). Notes are written by previously registered users. To register, the account must be older than six months and a verified phone number is required. Because anyone can participate, Notes are often described as the wisdom of the crowd and contrasted with fact-checks as an unbiased alternative. However, this interpretation overlooks the fact that the users who write Notes are not free of political views. Their assessments and comments may therefore be influenced by their own interests or ideological biases (Allen et al. 2022).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/Söder_Community_Note.png&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; height=&#34;700px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/img&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/Markus_Soeder/status/1879106313956765889&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt; with a community note that was rated as helpful and therefore published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Precisely because a single registration is enough to write Notes for all posts on X, this is not yet a sign of quality for their correctness. For this reason, registered users can not only write their own Notes, but also rate the Notes of others as helpful or not. To arrive at a final rating, X uses a so-called bridging algorithm. This algorithm takes into account the position of registered users on the political spectrum and requires contributors with different viewpoints to rate the note as helpful (Wojcik et al. 2022). This process is often successful in reflecting the political spectrum, but it also ensures that significantly fewer Notes are published than are actually written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-accounts-of-german-parties-and-politicians-receive-community-notes&#34;&gt;Which accounts of German parties and politicians receive Community Notes?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/Barplots.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;600px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt; Number of posts with Community Notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following, I present the results of the data analysis. In total, I analysed almost 9000 Notes, of which almost 1700 were considered helpful and therefore published. Figure 2a shows the accounts with the most Notes. Of all accounts on X, Markus Söder, the leader of the CSU and Chief Minister of Bavaria, received the most Notes. However, this changes when it comes to helpful Notes (Fig. 2b). Here, with the exception of Julian Reichelt, former editor-in-chief of Bild and founder of Nius, rather unknown accounts are among the top-ranked accounts. Political accounts, namely those of the CSU and Markus Söder, are only found from 8th place onwards. With this in mind, and also looking at Fig. 2c and Fig. 2d, we can see that the accounts with the most Notes and those with the most helpful Notes are in some cases very different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-parties-receive-the-most-community-notes&#34;&gt;Which parties receive the most Community Notes?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/Barplots_Parties.html&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;500px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt; Number of posts with Community Notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 3 shows the Notes of German politicians by party. Party scores are often strongly influenced by individual politicians. As shown in Figure 2, for the CSU it is mainly the official party account and that of Markus Söder. For the SPD it is mainly Ralf Stegner, member of the Bundestag, and Arno Gottschalk, financial policy spokesman for the Bremen parliamentary group. A rough analysis of the content shows that Stegner&amp;rsquo;s posts mainly relate to the Russian war in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As before, the ranking of most Notes differs if you only look at the helpful ones. The Greens lead the ranking of Notes, closely followe&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How behavioural sciences can promote truth, autonomy and democratic discourse online</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2020-behavioural/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/phillipp-2020-behavioural/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
