<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mobility | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/mobility/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/mobility/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>mobility</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2024 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>mobility</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/mobility/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inferring country-specific import risk of diseases from the world air transportation network</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2024-inferring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2024-inferring/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alles, was das Unterwegssein bremst, ist jetzt sinnvoll</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/press/zeitonline_2021_01_21/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/press/zeitonline_2021_01_21/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wir müssen an allen Ecken ganz massiv Kontakte reduzieren</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/press/rbb24_2021_01_15/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/press/rbb24_2021_01_15/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lockdown Monitor</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/lockdown_monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/lockdown_monitor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the context of the COVID-19 pandemic, daily updated, anonymized and aggregated mobility data
with high regional and temporal triggering has been analyzed at the RKI since March 2020 in order
to indirectly quantify the effect of lock and shutdown as well as easing measures and political
appeals, the data basis for quantitative To create a modeling of the pandemic and to capture regional
differences. In the project group P4 - Epidemiological Modeling of Infectious Diseases - at the RKI,
various digital technologies, network-theoretical methods and algorithms for the analysis of mobility
data were developed and implemented in order to analyze very extensive mobility data sets on a daily
basis and automatically. The Mobility Monitor (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.covid-19-mobility.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;www.covid-19-mobility.org&lt;/a&gt;) - an interactive, web-based
and daily updated platform - has been providing information on mobility in Germany since March 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regional resolution of the monitor is currently the district level in Germany. The monitor provides
regular reports with background analysis. The effects of the lock and shutdowns in spring and autumn 2020
on mobility were and will be analyzed, and the knowledge gained is used as a basis for decision-making
in health management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The present research project is based on the pilot project. The aim is to develop a comprehensive
lockdown monitor that provides a comprehensive and in-depth overview of mobility in Germany on a
daily basis and makes it available to decision-makers. By supplying significantly more finely
resolved mobility data, the anticipated lockdown monitor can resolve mobility around 100 times
better with a spatial resolution of up to 500m in city centers and 8km in rural areas. The time
resolution is increased to hourly updates. In this way, especially in areas with a high incidence,
e.g. in large cities, the effect of lockdown and relaxation measures can be recorded very precisely
and differentiated much better than before. The already developed platform of the mobility monitor
will serve as the basis for the implementation of the lockdown monitor. The lockdown monitor is
programmed modularly so that various web-based analysis modules can be embedded in other platforms
such as the COVID-19 dashboard for Germany and other monitoring tools, for example at the BMG.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pressekonferenz des RKI</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/press/youtube_2021_01_14/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/press/youtube_2021_01_14/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 - Event Horizon</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/covid-19-event-horizon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/covid-19-event-horizon/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hosts mobility and spatial spread of Rickettsia rickettsii</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/polo-2018-host/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/polo-2018-host/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact Monitor</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/contact_mobitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/contact_mobitor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How a pandemic develops depends on many factors: the biology of the pathogen, its susceptibility to external influences such as humidity and temperature, the success of vaccination campaigns, but most of all it is determined by contacts between individuals: transmissions occur primarily when people have contact with each other. The number of contacts thus gives us an insight into the course of the pandemic. Fewer contacts make it more difficult for the pathogen to spread through the population, whereas more contacts promote rapid spread. In the Contacts Monitor, we show the number of contacts in Germany over time. In the following, we explain how these contacts are measured from GPS data of cell phones.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 Mobility Monitor</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/mobility_monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/mobility_monitor/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
