<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Benjamin F. Maier | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/benjamin/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/authors/benjamin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Benjamin F. Maier</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/authors/benjamin/avatar_hu75d028ad25bdf51bdaa73cdb2c2faf27_248797_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Benjamin F. Maier</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/authors/benjamin/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for positive long- and short-term effects of vaccinations against COVID-19 in wearable sensor metrics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/wiedermann-2023-evidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/wiedermann-2023-evidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing global preparedness during an ongoing pandemic from partial and noisy data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2023-enhancing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/klamser-2023-enhancing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the impact of the Omicron infection wave in Germany</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-modeling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the share of SARS-CoV-2- immunologically naïve individuals in Germany up to June 2022</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-estimating/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2023-estimating/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out: Understanding the impact of digital contact tracing during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dct-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/dct-paper/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the impact of digital contact tracing during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/burdinski-2021-tracing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/burdinski-2021-tracing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper out: Germany’s fourth COVID-19 wave was mainly driven by the unvaccinated</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/role_of_vaccinated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/role_of_vaccinated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s43856-022-00176-7&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In this paper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we use a recently developed approach (the contribution matrix method) in combination with epidemiological data to estimate the contribution of vaccinated and unvaccinated populations to the current COVID-19 effective reproduction number &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt; in Germany. We find that a substantial fraction of reproduction is caused by unvaccinated individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pdf of the paper is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s43856-022-00176-7.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the majority of the German population was fully vaccinated at the time (about 65%), COVID-19 incidence started growing exponentially in October 2021 with about 41% of recorded new cases aged twelve or above being symptomatic breakthrough infections, presumably also contributing to the dynamics. So far, it remained elusive how significant this contribution was and whether targeted non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) may have stopped the amplification of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We develop and introduce a contribution matrix approach based on the next-generation matrix of a population-structured compartmental infectious disease model to derive contributions of respective inter- and intragroup infection pathways of unvaccinated and vaccinated subpopulations to the effective reproduction number and new infections, considering empirical data of vaccine efficacies against infection and transmission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we show that about 61%–76% of all new infections were caused by unvaccinated individuals and only 24%–39% were caused by the vaccinated. Furthermore, 32%–51% of new infections were likely caused by unvaccinated infecting other unvaccinated. Decreasing the transmissibility of the unvaccinated by, e. g. targeted NPIs, causes a steeper decrease in the effective reproduction number R than decreasing the transmissibility of vaccinated individuals, potentially leading to temporary epidemic control. Reducing contacts between vaccinated and unvaccinated individuals serves to decrease R in a similar manner as increasing vaccine uptake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A minority of the German population—the unvaccinated—is assumed to have caused the majority of new infections in the fall of 2021 in Germany. Our results highlight the importance of combined measures, such as vaccination campaigns and targeted contact reductions to achieve temporary epidemic control.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Germany’s fourth COVID-19 wave was mainly driven by the unvaccinated</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-germany/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-germany/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Enhancing global preparedness during an ongoing pandemic from partial and noisy data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Preprint Out: Modeling the impact of the Omicron infection wave in Germany</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/omicron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2021, the first case of SARS-CoV-2 “variant of concern” (VOC) B.1.1.529 (“Omicron”) was reported in Germany, alongside global reports of reduced vaccine efficacy against infections with this variant. The potential threat posed by the rapid spread of this variant in Germany remained, at the time, elusive.
We developed a variant-dependent population-averaged susceptible-exposed-infected-recovered (SEIR) infectious disease model. The model was calibrated on the observed fixation dynamics of the Omicron variant in December 2021, and allowed us to estimate potential courses of upcoming infection waves in Germany, focusing on the corresponding burden on intensive care units (ICUs) and the efficacy of contact reduction strategies. A maximum median incidence of approximately 300 000 (50% PI in 1000: [181,454], 95% PI in 1000: [55,804]) reported cases per day was expected with the median peak occurring in the mid of February 2022, reaching a cumulative Omicron case count of 16.5 million (50% PI in mio: [11.4, 21.3], 95% PI in mio: [4.1, 27.9]) until Apr 1, 2022. These figures were in line with the actual Omicron waves that were subsequently observed in Germany with respective peaks occurring in mid February (peak: 191k daily new cases) and mid March (peak: 230k daily new cases), cumulatively infecting 14.8 million individuals during the study period. The model peak incidence was observed to be highly sensitive to variations in the assumed generation time and decreased with shorter generation time. Low contact reductions were expected to lead to containment. Early, strict, and short contact reductions could have led to a strong “rebound” effect with high incidences after the end of the respective non-pharmaceutical interventions. Higher vaccine uptake would have led to a lower outbreak size. To ensure that ICU occupancy remained below maximum capacity, a relative risk of requiring ICU care of 10%–20% was necessary (after infection with Omicron vs. infection with Delta).
We expected a large cumulative number of infections with the VOC Omicron in Germany with ICU occupancy likely remaining below capacity nevertheless, even without additional non-pharmaceutical interventions. Our estimates were in line with the retrospectively observed waves. The results presented here informed legislation in Germany. The methodology developed in this study might be used to estimate the impact of future waves of COVID-19 or other infectious diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint: Estimating the distribution of COVID-19-susceptible, -recovered, and -vaccinated individuals in Germany up to April 2022</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/sero_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/sero_preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.04.19.22274030v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.04.19.22274030v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New preprint: Evidence for positive long- and short-term effects of vaccinations against COVID-19 in wearable sensor metrics -- Insights from the German Corona Data Donation Project</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/long_covid_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/long_covid_preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper we use physiological data collected in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://corona-datenspende.de/science/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;German Data Donation Project (Datenspende)&lt;/a&gt; to investigate the differential impact of vaccination on the effect that a COVID-19 infection has on &lt;strong&gt;resting heart rate&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;physical activity&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sleep&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02846&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02846&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abschätzung der Infektionswelle durch die SARS-CoV-2 VOC Omikron</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-omicron/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2022-omicron/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Die Pandemie wird durch fehlenden Impfschutz getrieben: Was ist zu tun?</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-pandemie/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-pandemie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;wichtig&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wichtig:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die hier beschriebenen wissenschaftlichen Ergebnisse beziehen sich auf die &lt;strong&gt;B.1.617.2&lt;/strong&gt; SARS-CoV-2 Variante (&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Delta&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;) und das Infektionsgeschehen Mitte November in Deutschland. Die Ergebnisse spiegeln nicht die Situation der Omicron-Welle (SARS-CoV-2-Variante &lt;strong&gt;B.1.1.529&lt;/strong&gt;) Anfang 2022 wieder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impfungen gehören du den wirksamsten Mitteln der Pandemiebekämpfung. Trotzdem sind die Impfraten im &lt;a href=&#34;https://ourworldindata.org/covid-vaccinations?country=OWID_WRL&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;deutschsprachigen Europa&lt;/a&gt; aktuell viel zu niedrig für eine effektive Eindämmung des Virus. In Deutschland waren am 22.11.2021 68% doppelt geimpft, obwohl das &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjH84v28rD0AhWJzKQKHfsXCJUQFnoECAUQAQ&amp;amp;url=https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/Infekt/EpidBull/Archiv/2021/27/Art_01.html&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0G9DqJ7ijemGlZYRwXrZbW&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RKI&lt;/a&gt; bereits im Juli 2021 empfahl, 85% der 12-59-Jährigen und 90% der Über-60-Jährigen zu impfen. Ähnlich schlecht sieht es in Österreich (65% vollständig geimpft) und der Schweiz (66%) aus. Auffrischungsimpfungen (Booster) zur Erhöhung der Impfeffektivität sind seit November in Deutschland &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/Kommissionen/STIKO/Empfehlungen/PM_2021-11-18.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;empfohlen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neue Berechnungen auf der Basis eines mathematischen Ansteckungsmodells &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; zeigen, dass eine effektive Erhöhung der Impfquote jedoch dringend notwendig ist: bei 8 bis 9 von 10 Ansteckungen mit COVID-19 ist mindestens eine ungeimpfte Person beteiligt. Das folgende Beispiel illustriert, dass aktuell der Großteil der Neuinfektionen durch fehlenden Impfschutz verursacht wird, obwohl ungeimpfte Personen nur ca. 32% der Bevölkerung ausmachen.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-abb1&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb1_hue3d634736fd43df10aac553ccb3f4083_157779_ccdfe103bc690c00c7c2fc9987d18c85.jpeg 400w,
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb1_hue3d634736fd43df10aac553ccb3f4083_157779_ad3a9845a07c9004e239652e5336d0a3.jpeg 760w,
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb1_hue3d634736fd43df10aac553ccb3f4083_157779_1200x1200_fit_q75_lanczos.jpeg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb1_hue3d634736fd43df10aac553ccb3f4083_157779_ccdfe103bc690c00c7c2fc9987d18c85.jpeg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Abbildung zeigt, wie ungeimpfte und geimpfte Personen anteilig an der Verbreitung von COVID-19 beteiligt sind (laut Modellschätzungen). Man stelle sich eine Gruppe von Infizierten vor. Angenommen, diese Gruppe hat 100 Ansteckungen verursacht. In der oberen Grafik (A) wird eine Impfeffektivität von 72% bei Erwachsenen und 92% bei Kindern und
Jugendlichen angenommen. Dann sehen die 100 Ansteckungen folgendermaßen aus: 51
von den 100 Angesteckten sind Ungeimpfte, die von anderen Ungeimpften infiziert wurden. 25 sind Geimpfte, die von Ungeimpften infiziert wurden. Es wurden also 76 Personen von Ungeimpften angesteckt. Der Anteil der Leute, der durch Geimpfte angesteckt wird, ist erheblich kleiner: 15 Angesteckte sind Ungeimpfte, die von Geimpften angesteckt wurden und 9 sind Geimpfte, die von Geimpften angesteckt wurden. Es wurden also lediglich 24 Personen von Geimpften angesteckt. 91 von 100 Ansteckungen entstehen mit Beteiligung mindestens einer Person ohne Impfschutz.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-abb2&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb2_hucbf4ebb6e9f66eebdac69406ef95838f_156632_808930b7bcafa70c4f5a142c5d509e80.jpeg 400w,
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb2_hucbf4ebb6e9f66eebdac69406ef95838f_156632_76d6c27b8cacea6619e2388996f3b37f.jpeg 760w,
               /publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb2_hucbf4ebb6e9f66eebdac69406ef95838f_156632_1200x1200_fit_q75_lanczos.jpeg 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-pandemie/abb2_hucbf4ebb6e9f66eebdac69406ef95838f_156632_808930b7bcafa70c4f5a142c5d509e80.jpeg&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Um zu verstehen, ob neue Ansteckungen auch durch fehlenden Impfschutz getrieben werden, wenn die Impfung nur eine geringe Effektivität hat, wurde in einem zweiten Beispiel eine geringere Impfeffektivität angenommen &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In der unteren Grafik wird eine Impfeffektivität von 50% bei über 60ig-Jährigen, 60% bei Erwachsenen bis 59 Jahren und 60% bei Kindern und Jugendlichen bis 17 Jahren angenommen. Dann sehen die 100 Infektionen folgendermaßen aus: 38 von den 100 Angesteckten sind Ungeimpfte, die von anderen Ungeimpften infiziert wurden. 29 sind Geimpfte, die von Ungeimpften infiziert wurden. Es wurden also 67 Personen von Ungeimpften angesteckt. Der Anteil der Leute, der durch Geimpfte angesteckt wird, ist erheblich kleiner: 17 Angesteckte sind Ungeimpfte, die von Geimpften angesteckt wurden und 16 sind Geimpfte, die von Geimpften angesteckt wurden. Es wurden also lediglich 33 Neuinfizierte von Geimpften angesteckt. 84 von 100 Ansteckungen entstehen mit Beteiligung mindestens einer Person ohne Impfschutz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;daraus-ergibt-sich&#34;&gt;Daraus ergibt sich:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An 8 bis 9 von 10 Ansteckungen sind Personen ohne Impfschutz beteiligt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Je effektiver der Impfschutz, desto weniger Ansteckungen werden durch geimpfte Personen verursacht.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Die Dynamik der Pandemie wird aktuell also stark durch fehlenden oder nachlassenden, weniger effektiven Impfschutz getrieben.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;daher-empfiehlt-sich&#34;&gt;Daher empfiehlt sich:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impfquote effektiv erhöhen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effektivität des Impfschutzes erhöhen, z.B. durch Boostern.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kontakte reduzieren, v.a. zwischen ungeimpften Personen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ohne zusätzliche Maßnahmen ist keine baldige Besserung der Impfquote zu erwarten, da die Zuwachsrate der Impfkampagne seit Juni 2021 &lt;a href=&#34;http://impfdashboard.de/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;stagniert&lt;/a&gt;. Für zusätzliche Maßnahmen zur Steigerung der Impfquote besteht die Herausforderung, dass ein Großteil der ungeimpften Personen schwer erreichbar ist - z.B. laut der &lt;a href=&#34;https://projekte.uni-erfurt.de/cosmo2020/web/summary/56/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;COSMO-Studie&lt;/a&gt; sind 30% der Ungeimpften zögerlich, 54% sagen, sie wollen sich auf keinen Fall impfen lassen (Stand November 2021). Vor- und Nachteile eine Impfpflicht sollten &lt;a href=&#34;https://psyarxiv.com/pmx3w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;diskutiert werden&lt;/a&gt;. Maßnahmen, die schnell die Kontakte reduzieren, sollten zum Brechen der 4. Welle implementiert werden, da selbst ein schneller Anstieg der Impfrate erst mittelfristig weitere Wellen verhindern, nicht aber die aktuelle Welle brechen kann.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kontakt:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:bfmaier@physik.hu-berlin.de&#34;&gt;bfmaier@physik.hu-berlin.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preprint:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/publication/maier-2021-germany/maier-2021-germany.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Germany’s current COVID-19 crisis is mainly driven by the unvaccinated&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das theoretische Framework hinter diesen Berechnungen heisst Contribution Matrix. Die Berechnungen sind detailliert hier beschrieben: &lt;a href=&#34;https://rocs.hu-berlin.de/publication/maier-2021-germany/maier-2021-germany.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://rocs.hu-berlin.de/publication/maier-2021- germany/maier-2021-germany.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beide Szenarien gehen von folgenden aktuellen Impfraten pro Altersgruppe aus: 0-11 = 0%, 12-17 = 40%, 18-59 = 72%, 60+ = 85%. Über die tatsächliche Impfeffektivität besteht wissenschaftliche Unsicherheit. Daher werden zwei verschiedene Szenarien angenommen. In Szenario A wird eine hohe Impfeffektivität von 92% bei Kindern und 72% bei Erwachsenen angenommen. Dies entspricht den Effektivitäten der Periode Oktober 2021 für symptomatisches COVID-19 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/InfAZ/N/Neuartiges_Coronavirus/Situationsberichte/Gesamt.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RKI Situationsbericht vom 11.11.2021&lt;/a&gt;). Im Modell werden jedoch Impfeffektivitäten gegen Infektion angenommen, die üblicherweise geringer sind als gegen symptomatisches COVID-19. Diese Effektivitätsschätzung ist daher eine optimistische Schätzung und dient dies als mögliche Obergrenze. Die niedrigeren Impfeffktivitäten gegen Infektion (Szenario B) sind in Übereinstimmung mit Daten aus Großbritannien gewählt (50% bei über 60ig-Jährigen, 60% bei Erwachsenen bis 59 Jahren und 60% bei Kindern und Jugendlichen bis 17 Jahren). In &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abm0620&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Großbritannien&lt;/a&gt; wurde vorwiegend mit AstraZeneca geimpft. Dieser Impfstoff gilt in der Literatur als weniger effektiv. Daher dienen diese Werte im Modell als Schätzung für niedrige Impfeffektivität gegen Infektion. Die Ansteckungs-Zahlen beschreiben die geschätzten Anteile der Infektionswege an der totalen effektiven Reproduktionszahl (Reff). Zum Zeitpunkt dieser Berechnungen lag R etwa bei &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/robert-koch-institut/SARS-CoV-2-Nowcasting_und_-R-Schaetzung/blob/main/Nowcast_R_aktuell.csv&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;1,2&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Digital contact tracing contributes little to COVID-19 outbreak containment</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/tracing_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/tracing_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our preprint &amp;ldquo;Digital contact tracing contributes little to COVID-19 outbreak containment&amp;rdquo; is out and available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As digital contact tracing apps raised the hope that they may be efficient enough to contain outbreaks
without falling back to harsher NPIs, we analyzed its success. Relying on empirical results, we find
an expected outbreak size reduction on the order of a few percent at best. While the intervention
may aid the manual tracing process, we argue that countries should concentrate on other means to contain
COVID-19 outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital contact tracing applications have been introduced in many countries to aid in the containment of
COVID-19 outbreaks. Initially, enthusiasm was high regarding their implementation as a non-pharmaceutical
intervention (NPI). Yet, no country was able to prevent larger outbreaks without falling back to harsher NPIs,
and the total effect of digital contact tracing remains elusive. Based on the results of empirical studies and
modeling efforts, we show that digital contact tracing apps might have prevented cases on the order of single-digit
percentages up until now, at best. We show that this poor impact can be attributed to a combination of low
participation rates, a non-flexible reliance on symptom-based testing, low engagement of participants, and
delays between testing and test result upload. We find that contact tracing does not change the epidemic
threshold and exclusively prevents more cases during the supercritical phase of an epidemic, making it unfit
as a tool to prevent outbreaks. Locally clustered contact structures may increase the intervention’s efficacy,
but only if the number of contacts per individual is homogeneously distributed, a condition usually not found in
contact networks.  Our results suggest that policy makers cannot rely on digital contact tracing to contain
outbreaks of COVID-19 or similar diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact Index Monitor</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/contactindex-monitor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/contactindex-monitor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;contact-index-monitor&#34;&gt;Contact Index Monitor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;width: 100%; height: 450px; border: 1px solid #ddd; margin: 20px 0;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe 
    src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/viz/contactindex-monitor/&#34; 
    width=&#34;100%&#34; 
    height=&#34;100%&#34; 
    frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
    style=&#34;border: none;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How a pandemic develops depends on many factors: the biology of the pathogen, its susceptibility to external influences such as humidity and temperature, but most of all it is determined by contacts between individuals: transmissions occur primarily when people have contact with each other. The number of contacts thus gives us an insight into the course of the pandemic. Fewer contacts make it more difficult for the pathogen to spread through the population, whereas more contacts promote rapid spread. In the Contacts Monitor, we show the number of contacts and its variation in Germany over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;width: 100%; height: 1000px; border: 1px solid #ddd; margin: 20px 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe 
    src=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/viz/contactindex-monitor/states.html&#34; 
    width=&#34;100%&#34; 
    height=&#34;100%&#34; 
    frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
    scrolling=&#34;no&#34;
    style=&#34;border: none; overflow: hidden;
    onload=&#34;this.contentDocument.body.style.overflow=&#39;hidden&#39;;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-potential/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2021-potential/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/vaccination_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are happy that our preprint &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2102.13600.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential benefits of delaying the second mRNA COVID-19 vaccine dose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is out and available on &lt;em&gt;arxiv.org&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a very constructive and effective collaborative effort, lead by our &lt;a href=&#34;https://synosys.github.io/author/dr.-benjamin-f.-maier/&#34;&gt;Ben Maier&lt;/a&gt;, who did all the heavy lifting, and valuable contributions by the teams of Cornelia Betsch, Michael Meyer-Hermann and by Karl Lauterbach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell we evaluate and compare different vaccination strageties of COVID-19 mRNA-vaccines in high-risk groups in Germany and show that a flexible scheduling of the second vaccine dose can potentially be the way to go. If you are interested in the details, have a look at the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vaccination against COVID-19 with the recently approved mRNA vaccines BNT162b2 (BioNTech/Pfizer) and mRNA-1273 (Moderna) is currently underway in a large number of countries. However, high incidence rates and rapidly spreading SARS-CoV-2 variants are concerning. In combination with acute supply deficits in Europe in early 2021, the question arises of whether stretching the vaccine, for instance by delaying the second dose, can make a significant contribution to preventing deaths, despite associated risks such as lower vaccine efficacy, the potential emergence of escape mutants, enhancement, waning immunity, reduced social acceptance of off-label vaccination, and liability shifts. A quantitative epidemiological assessment of risks and benefits of non-standard vaccination protocols remains elusive. To clarify the situation and to provide a quantitative epidemiological foundation we develop a stochastic epidemiological model that integrates specific vaccine rollout protocols into a risk-group structured infectious disease dynamical model. Using the situation and conditions in Germany as a reference system, we show that delaying the second vaccine dose is expected to prevent deaths in the four to five digit range, should the incidence resurge. We show that this considerable public health benefit relies on the fact that both mRNA vaccines provide substantial protection against severe COVID-19 and death beginning 12 to 14 days after the first dose. The benefits of protocol change are attenuated should vaccine compliance decrease substantially. To quantify the impact of protocol change on vaccination adherence we performed a large-scale online survey. We find that, in Germany, changing vaccination protocols may lead to small reductions in vaccination intention. In sum, we therefore expect the benefits of a strategy change to remain substantial and stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epipack</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/epipack/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/epipack/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 lockdown induces disease-mitigating structural changes in mobility networks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2020-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/schlosser-2020-covid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effective containment explains subexponential growth in recent confirmed COVID-19 cases in China</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2020-effective/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2020-effective/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Netwulf</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/netwulf/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/netwulf/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comprehensive integrated NGS-based surveillance and contact-network modeling unravels transmission dynamics of vancomycin-resistant enterococci in a high-risk population within a tertiary care hospital</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/neumann-2020-comprehensive/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/neumann-2020-comprehensive/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modular hierarchical and power-law small-world networks bear structural optima for minimal first passage times and cover time</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2019-modular/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2019-modular/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cover time for random walks on arbitrary complex networks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2017-cover/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/maier-2017-cover/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
