<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>biology | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/biology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/biology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>biology</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>biology</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/biology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Complex Systems</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/teaching/complex-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/teaching/complex-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Opal: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bildungsportal.sachsen.de/opal/auth/RepositoryEntry/50920947715?4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Link here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time (Lecture): Mondays and Tuesdays, 18:30 – 20:00&lt;br&gt;
Time (Seminar): Wednesdays and Thursdays, 18:30 – 20:00&lt;br&gt;
Time (Lab Course): Jan. 5th - Jan. 15th, 2026&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location: S7A-204&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Module: M0500-31W2 (Molecular Biology and Biotechnology)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language: English&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assessment: presentation, written exam, and participation in the lab course&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course offers an overview and basic understanding of complex dynamic phenomena in biological, physical and social systems. The focus is on biological systems but with a particular emphasis on how phenomena observed in biological systems are related to systems outside of biology. For example: Are the dynamic patterns observed in flocking birds and schooling fish related to pedestrian dynamics, or political polarization? What are the underlying principles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complexity science is about unraveling these underlying principles that drive a complex phenomenon and trying to construct models based on these underlying principles that can reproduce the basic properties of a system with as few ingredients as possible. Complex systems come in different flavors and can be associated with different fundamental phenomena and concepts, each of which will be covered in the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these concepts and phenomena occur and are applied across a broad range of fields. Here’s a list of those that will be covered in the course:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chaotic Dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Synchronization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pattern Formation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Critical Phenomena &amp;amp; Tipping Points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Growth Processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collective Behavior&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complex Networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fractals &amp;amp; Self-Similarity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cooperative Systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lecture will also cover a number of basic theoretical modeling methods, analysis tools and techniques that are required to understand and appreciate the richness and beauty of complex systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Podcast Episode featuring Dirk Brockmann: “Survival of the Nettest” – Why Nature Thrives on Cooperation</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/podcast_episode_dirk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/podcast_episode_dirk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We usually associate evolution with fierce competition: the strong overpower the weak, the fast outrun the slow, and only the best make it to the finish line. “Survival of the fittest” – that’s how the story goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if that’s a fundamental misunderstanding?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the newest episode of &lt;em&gt;Down the Rabbit Hole – Der TU Dresden Biologie Podcast&lt;/em&gt;, Prof. &lt;strong&gt;Dirk Brockmann&lt;/strong&gt; joins hosts &lt;strong&gt;Oliver Zierau&lt;/strong&gt;, and biology students &lt;strong&gt;Leonie&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Cosima&lt;/strong&gt; to unpack the deeper meaning behind one of the most quoted — and misinterpreted — phrases in science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because when Darwin wrote “fittest,” he didn’t mean the strongest or the most aggressive. He meant the most &lt;strong&gt;adapted&lt;/strong&gt;, and often, the most &lt;strong&gt;cooperative&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this lively and insightful conversation, Dirk talks about how this realization led him to write his latest book, &lt;em&gt;“Survival of the Nettest: Wie die Natur durch Kooperation unsere Welt gestaltet.”&lt;/em&gt; Drawing on ideas from &lt;strong&gt;network science&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;evolutionary biology&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;complex systems&lt;/strong&gt;, he paints a compelling picture of how &lt;strong&gt;connection&lt;/strong&gt;, not isolation, is the real driver of survival and resilience — in ecosystems, in human societies, and in our digital world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🎧 The episode is in German.&lt;br&gt;
👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/episode/5qg5tXkDIdAJYgof5GLgK2?si=GDBJg4IlQESRqoPK34_CXg&amp;amp;nd=1&amp;amp;dlsi=868d3484bb2e4a3d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tune in on Spotify&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
