<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>populism | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/populism/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/populism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>populism</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>populism</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/populism/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Communicating Smarter Than Populism? Dirk Brockmann on Science, Emotion, and the Power of Cooperation</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/communicating_populism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/communicating_populism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How can science keep up in a world where catchy headlines and emotional soundbites dominate the public debate? In a recent interview, SynoSys Director &lt;strong&gt;Dirk Brockmann&lt;/strong&gt; shares his take, and it’s both clear-eyed and hopeful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;His message:&lt;/strong&gt; People can handle complexity. What they need is time, space, and stories that stick. Rather than trying to out-simplify populism, science should learn to communicate in a way that’s both emotionally engaging and intellectually honest. That means building strong, vivid images — not just showing data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dirk also talks about the role of &lt;strong&gt;diversity and cooperation&lt;/strong&gt; — in nature, where innovation often comes from unlikely alliances, but also in interdisciplinary research and science communication. And yes, sometimes it’s okay to ask the “naive” questions. That’s how real dialogue starts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At &lt;strong&gt;SynoSys&lt;/strong&gt;, this resonates deeply with what we do: bringing together systems thinkers from different fields and creating new ways of understanding complex realities — and sharing them with the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wissenschaftskommunikation.de/herr-brockmann-wie-kommuniziert-man-klueger-als-der-populismus-90197/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the full interview (in German)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
