<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Network Science | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/network-science/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/network-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Network Science</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>Network Science</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/network-science/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>SynoSys Coordinates National Research Project DREAM EP</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/national_research_project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/national_research_project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SynoSys will coordinate &lt;strong&gt;DREAM EP&lt;/strong&gt;, a national research initiative to advance the science of pandemic forecasting. The project brings together leading institutions across Germany to rethink how we model the spread of respiratory diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DREAM EP&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Data-informed Responsive Epidemic Analysis and Multiscale-Modelling for Epidemic Preparedness&lt;/em&gt;) investigates how infection dynamics interact with human mobility, behavior, and societal response. The project builds an adaptive model ecosystem that integrates high-resolution data on contact networks, virus evolution, mobility flows, and global air traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal: &lt;strong&gt;to detect critical shifts earlier, improve predictive accuracy, and support more effective responses in future respiratory pandemics.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At SynoSys, we contribute deep expertise in &lt;strong&gt;network science, complex systems, and data-driven modeling&lt;/strong&gt;. Together with our partners, we will apply innovative methods from &lt;strong&gt;machine learning, causal inference, and adaptive network theory&lt;/strong&gt; to better understand the feedback loop between disease dynamics and human behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The total project volume is &lt;strong&gt;€1.8 million&lt;/strong&gt;. SynoSys will receive &lt;strong&gt;€150,000&lt;/strong&gt; in the initial funding phase, with the option for a second tranche of &lt;strong&gt;€150,000&lt;/strong&gt; if the project is extended. DREAM EP is scheduled to run from &lt;strong&gt;January 2026 to December 2027&lt;/strong&gt;, with a possible extension through &lt;strong&gt;2029&lt;/strong&gt; pending successful midterm evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;bmftr-logo-funding.png&#34; alt=&#34;BMFTR funding logo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“Survival of the Nettest” Wins Science Book of the Year</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/survival_nettest/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/survival_nettest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to share that &lt;em&gt;Survival of the Nettest&lt;/em&gt; by Dirk Brockmann has been named &lt;strong&gt;Science Book of the Year 2025&lt;/strong&gt; in the category &lt;strong&gt;“Overview”&lt;/strong&gt;. The award honors books that provide exceptional clarity in presenting complex topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this interdisciplinary work, Dirk explores a simple yet powerful idea: that &lt;strong&gt;cooperation—rather than competition—drives the major innovations in evolution&lt;/strong&gt;. From the microbial world to complex ecosystems, he illustrates how symbiotic relationships have shaped life on Earth and continue to influence our understanding of individuality, biology, and society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book offers a thought-provoking synthesis of &lt;strong&gt;biology, systems thinking, and network science&lt;/strong&gt;, accessible to readers both within and beyond the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Congratulations to Dirk on this well-deserved recognition.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Network Structure Shapes Evolutionary Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/network_structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/network_structure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our colleague &lt;strong&gt;Adrian Zachariae&lt;/strong&gt; has published a new preprint on how network structure shapes evolutionary dynamics in asexual populations. The study examines clonal interference the competition between beneficial mutations, and demonstrates that this process is strongly influenced by the topology of the underlying network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through computational modelling and a novel analytical approach inspired by epidemic research, Adrian and his co-authors show how mutation rates and network geometry interact to generate distinct evolutionary regimes. These regimes determine where high-fitness strains emerge and how they spread across the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings offer new perspectives on how spatial heterogeneity affects adaptation, with relevance for understanding pathogen evolution, conservation biology, and other complex systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.10.20.683208v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the preprint on bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Podcast Episode featuring Dirk Brockmann: “Survival of the Nettest” – Why Nature Thrives on Cooperation</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/podcast_episode_dirk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/podcast_episode_dirk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We usually associate evolution with fierce competition: the strong overpower the weak, the fast outrun the slow, and only the best make it to the finish line. “Survival of the fittest” – that’s how the story goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if that’s a fundamental misunderstanding?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the newest episode of &lt;em&gt;Down the Rabbit Hole – Der TU Dresden Biologie Podcast&lt;/em&gt;, Prof. &lt;strong&gt;Dirk Brockmann&lt;/strong&gt; joins hosts &lt;strong&gt;Oliver Zierau&lt;/strong&gt;, and biology students &lt;strong&gt;Leonie&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Cosima&lt;/strong&gt; to unpack the deeper meaning behind one of the most quoted — and misinterpreted — phrases in science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because when Darwin wrote “fittest,” he didn’t mean the strongest or the most aggressive. He meant the most &lt;strong&gt;adapted&lt;/strong&gt;, and often, the most &lt;strong&gt;cooperative&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this lively and insightful conversation, Dirk talks about how this realization led him to write his latest book, &lt;em&gt;“Survival of the Nettest: Wie die Natur durch Kooperation unsere Welt gestaltet.”&lt;/em&gt; Drawing on ideas from &lt;strong&gt;network science&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;evolutionary biology&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;complex systems&lt;/strong&gt;, he paints a compelling picture of how &lt;strong&gt;connection&lt;/strong&gt;, not isolation, is the real driver of survival and resilience — in ecosystems, in human societies, and in our digital world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🎧 The episode is in German.&lt;br&gt;
👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/episode/5qg5tXkDIdAJYgof5GLgK2?si=GDBJg4IlQESRqoPK34_CXg&amp;amp;nd=1&amp;amp;dlsi=868d3484bb2e4a3d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tune in on Spotify&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breaking Boundaries: Prof. Brockmann’s Vision for Complexity Research</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/breaking_boundaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/breaking_boundaries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On February 6, 2025, Professor Dirk Brockmann, head of our Center Synergy of Systems, delivered his university-wide inaugural lecture at TU Dresden, attracting over 100 attendees from various disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the intriguing title &amp;ldquo;Doing Science Like a Fungus – Complexity Research in the 21st Century&amp;rdquo;, Dirk Brockmann provided fascinating insights into complex systems and the hidden rules that govern social and natural phenomena. He emphasized the importance of interdisciplinary research, combining methods from physics, biology, and social sciences to better understand and address pressing global challenges. &lt;img src=&#34;featured2.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Brockman-with Audience&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One particularly interesting aspect of his lecture was his discussion on the connection between science and magic. He explained that when people witness something they perceive as magical—something they believed to be impossible—it sharpens their senses and heightens their awareness. This, he argued, is precisely what scientists must do in their research: approach the unknown with a sense of wonder, question assumptions, and stay open to unexpected discoveries. Just as magic challenges our understanding of reality, scientific breakthroughs emerge when we push beyond the boundaries of what we think we know. Doing science with a compass rather than a map.
&lt;img src=&#34;featured3.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Brockman-with Audience&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event, held at the Fritz-Foerster-Bau of TU Dresden, provided an engaging platform for discussions, followed by a lively Q&amp;amp;A session and networking opportunity.
Prof. Brockmann’s inspiring lecture set the tone for his future work at SynoSys, demonstrating how complexity science can drive impactful research and innovative solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who missed the event, the full lecture is available online: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iwMYuq4np6Y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Watch here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preprint out: Enhancing global preparedness during an ongoing pandemic from partial and noisy data</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/old_news/global_preparedness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The preprint is available here:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.08.19.22278981v1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
