<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine Learning | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/machine-learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Machine Learning</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/machine-learning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>SynoSys Coordinates National Research Project DREAM EP</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/national_research_project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/national_research_project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SynoSys will coordinate &lt;strong&gt;DREAM EP&lt;/strong&gt;, a national research initiative to advance the science of pandemic forecasting. The project brings together leading institutions across Germany to rethink how we model the spread of respiratory diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DREAM EP&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Data-informed Responsive Epidemic Analysis and Multiscale-Modelling for Epidemic Preparedness&lt;/em&gt;) investigates how infection dynamics interact with human mobility, behavior, and societal response. The project builds an adaptive model ecosystem that integrates high-resolution data on contact networks, virus evolution, mobility flows, and global air traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal: &lt;strong&gt;to detect critical shifts earlier, improve predictive accuracy, and support more effective responses in future respiratory pandemics.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At SynoSys, we contribute deep expertise in &lt;strong&gt;network science, complex systems, and data-driven modeling&lt;/strong&gt;. Together with our partners, we will apply innovative methods from &lt;strong&gt;machine learning, causal inference, and adaptive network theory&lt;/strong&gt; to better understand the feedback loop between disease dynamics and human behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The total project volume is &lt;strong&gt;€1.8 million&lt;/strong&gt;. SynoSys will receive &lt;strong&gt;€150,000&lt;/strong&gt; in the initial funding phase, with the option for a second tranche of &lt;strong&gt;€150,000&lt;/strong&gt; if the project is extended. DREAM EP is scheduled to run from &lt;strong&gt;January 2026 to December 2027&lt;/strong&gt;, with a possible extension through &lt;strong&gt;2029&lt;/strong&gt; pending successful midterm evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;bmftr-logo-funding.png&#34; alt=&#34;BMFTR funding logo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
