<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Complexity Research | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/complexity-research/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/complexity-research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Complexity Research</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>Complexity Research</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/complexity-research/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breaking Boundaries: Prof. Brockmann’s Vision for Complexity Research</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/breaking_boundaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/breaking_boundaries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On February 6, 2025, Professor Dirk Brockmann, head of our Center Synergy of Systems, delivered his university-wide inaugural lecture at TU Dresden, attracting over 100 attendees from various disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the intriguing title &amp;ldquo;Doing Science Like a Fungus – Complexity Research in the 21st Century&amp;rdquo;, Dirk Brockmann provided fascinating insights into complex systems and the hidden rules that govern social and natural phenomena. He emphasized the importance of interdisciplinary research, combining methods from physics, biology, and social sciences to better understand and address pressing global challenges. &lt;img src=&#34;featured2.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Brockman-with Audience&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One particularly interesting aspect of his lecture was his discussion on the connection between science and magic. He explained that when people witness something they perceive as magical—something they believed to be impossible—it sharpens their senses and heightens their awareness. This, he argued, is precisely what scientists must do in their research: approach the unknown with a sense of wonder, question assumptions, and stay open to unexpected discoveries. Just as magic challenges our understanding of reality, scientific breakthroughs emerge when we push beyond the boundaries of what we think we know. Doing science with a compass rather than a map.
&lt;img src=&#34;featured3.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Brockman-with Audience&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event, held at the Fritz-Foerster-Bau of TU Dresden, provided an engaging platform for discussions, followed by a lively Q&amp;amp;A session and networking opportunity.
Prof. Brockmann’s inspiring lecture set the tone for his future work at SynoSys, demonstrating how complexity science can drive impactful research and innovative solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who missed the event, the full lecture is available online: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iwMYuq4np6Y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Watch here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
