<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Post-exertional malaise | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/post-exertional-malaise/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/post-exertional-malaise/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Post-exertional malaise</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>Post-exertional malaise</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/post-exertional-malaise/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our Recent Paper Unveils Breakthrough Insights into Fatigue Symptoms in Post-COVID Syndrome and ME/CFS</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/post_covid-syndrome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/post_covid-syndrome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are excited to share the results of our recent study, in which we report new insights into Post-exertional Malaise (PEM), a severe condition where physical activity amplifies symptoms in people with Post-COVID Syndrome (PCC) and Myalgic Encephalomyelitis/Chronic Fatigue Syndrome (ME/CFS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our study highlights that even everyday activities, such as walking or light exertion, can significantly increase symptoms in affected patients. The root cause is an impaired ability of the body to utilize oxygen efficiently. Normally, cells utilize oxygen for energy production. However, in patients with PCC and ME/CFS, this process is disrupted, causing rapid exhaustion and muscle fatigue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also found that many patients exhibit ongoing immune activation, as if their bodies are still fighting an infection long after recovery from their COVID-19. This immune response contributes to the impaired oxygen utilization and amplifies fatigue and other symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are excited because we believe that our findings may open up new pathways for developing effective treatments. Our research suggests that careful management of physical activity, including avoiding overexertion, could be key to preventing symptom flare-ups and to improving daily life for affected patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are excited about the potential impact of this study and are confident that it offers hope for those struggling with the long-lasting effects of PCC and ME/CFS. You can read the full paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s15010-024-02386-8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards an understanding of physical activity-induced post-exertional malaise: Insights into microvascular alterations and immunometabolic interactions in post-COVID condition and myalgic encephalomyelitis/chronic fatigue syndrome</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/publication/haunhorst-2024-towards/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/publication/haunhorst-2024-towards/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
