<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>evolution | SynoSys</title>
    <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/evolution/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://synosys.github.io/tag/evolution/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>evolution</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 Center Synergy of Systems</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://synosys.github.io/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>evolution</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/tag/evolution/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>“Survival of the Nettest” Wins Science Book of the Year</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/survival_nettest/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/survival_nettest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to share that &lt;em&gt;Survival of the Nettest&lt;/em&gt; by Dirk Brockmann has been named &lt;strong&gt;Science Book of the Year 2025&lt;/strong&gt; in the category &lt;strong&gt;“Overview”&lt;/strong&gt;. The award honors books that provide exceptional clarity in presenting complex topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this interdisciplinary work, Dirk explores a simple yet powerful idea: that &lt;strong&gt;cooperation—rather than competition—drives the major innovations in evolution&lt;/strong&gt;. From the microbial world to complex ecosystems, he illustrates how symbiotic relationships have shaped life on Earth and continue to influence our understanding of individuality, biology, and society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book offers a thought-provoking synthesis of &lt;strong&gt;biology, systems thinking, and network science&lt;/strong&gt;, accessible to readers both within and beyond the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Congratulations to Dirk on this well-deserved recognition.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Podcast Episode featuring Dirk Brockmann: “Survival of the Nettest” – Why Nature Thrives on Cooperation</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/news/podcast_episode_dirk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/news/podcast_episode_dirk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We usually associate evolution with fierce competition: the strong overpower the weak, the fast outrun the slow, and only the best make it to the finish line. “Survival of the fittest” – that’s how the story goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if that’s a fundamental misunderstanding?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the newest episode of &lt;em&gt;Down the Rabbit Hole – Der TU Dresden Biologie Podcast&lt;/em&gt;, Prof. &lt;strong&gt;Dirk Brockmann&lt;/strong&gt; joins hosts &lt;strong&gt;Oliver Zierau&lt;/strong&gt;, and biology students &lt;strong&gt;Leonie&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Cosima&lt;/strong&gt; to unpack the deeper meaning behind one of the most quoted — and misinterpreted — phrases in science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because when Darwin wrote “fittest,” he didn’t mean the strongest or the most aggressive. He meant the most &lt;strong&gt;adapted&lt;/strong&gt;, and often, the most &lt;strong&gt;cooperative&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this lively and insightful conversation, Dirk talks about how this realization led him to write his latest book, &lt;em&gt;“Survival of the Nettest: Wie die Natur durch Kooperation unsere Welt gestaltet.”&lt;/em&gt; Drawing on ideas from &lt;strong&gt;network science&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;evolutionary biology&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;complex systems&lt;/strong&gt;, he paints a compelling picture of how &lt;strong&gt;connection&lt;/strong&gt;, not isolation, is the real driver of survival and resilience — in ecosystems, in human societies, and in our digital world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🎧 The episode is in German.&lt;br&gt;
👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/episode/5qg5tXkDIdAJYgof5GLgK2?si=GDBJg4IlQESRqoPK34_CXg&amp;amp;nd=1&amp;amp;dlsi=868d3484bb2e4a3d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tune in on Spotify&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clonal Interference in Heterogeneous Networks</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/clonal_interference/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/clonal_interference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our research group explores the intricate relationship between complex environmental structures and evolutionary processes, focusing on clonal interference in asexual populations. We aim to understand how organisms adapt in heterogeneous, network-like environments that closely resemble real-world scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clonal interference (CI) occurs in asexual populations when multiple beneficial mutations arise and compete, unable to combine through recombination. While CI has been studied in well-mixed or simple spatial structures, its behavior in complex, heterogeneous environments remains largely unexplored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;optional_cool.gif&#34; alt=&#34;cool gif&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key Research Aims:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding CI in Highly Heterogeneous Environments: We investigate how diverse network topologies influence clonal interference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying Key Structural Components: We aim to pinpoint specific elements of network structures that significantly impact adaptive processes, understanding which features promote faster adaptation and which areas are likely sources of adaptive mutations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shaping and Controlling Adaptive Evolution: By understanding how network structures influence evolution, we seek to develop strategies for potentially guiding adaptive processes in complex environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing Analytical Tools: We&amp;rsquo;re working to create and refine mathematical and computational tools that effectively model and predict evolutionary dynamics in intricate systems, bridging network theory, evolutionary biology, and complex systems science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The insights gained from our research have potential applications across a wide range of fields. In epidemiology, our understanding of how pathogens evolve in structured host populations could form more effective disease management strategies. Conservation biologists might use our findings to guide habitat management practices, supporting species adaptation and resilience in fragmented environments. Our work could also lead to improved bioprocess designs by accounting for how environmental structure affects microbial evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond these direct applications, the principles we uncover might have broader, more speculative implications. For instance, our approaches to mutation spread in biological networks could provide insights into how content goes viral on social media platforms with diverse user structures. The competition between genetic strains in our research might elucidate how ideas, innovations and cultural practices propagate through social and professional networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we continue to explore the intricate interplay between network complexity and evolutionary dynamics, we&amp;rsquo;re not merely advancing theoretical knowledge. We&amp;rsquo;re developing a deeper, more nuanced understanding of how adaptation occurs in complex systems. This research has the potential to open new avenues for managing and harnessing evolutionary processes in various fields, spanning from biology to the social sciences. By bridging the gap between network theory and evolutionary biology, we&amp;rsquo;re paving the way for a more comprehensive understanding of how information – be it genetic, cultural, or technological – spreads and competes in our interconnected world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fungal Growth</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/fungal_growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/fungal_growth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Fungi interact in a mycorrhizal symbiosis with plants or are simple decomposers of organic matter.
In this project, we investigate the growth of filamentous fungi by creating and investigating mathematical growth models.
We cooperate with experimental biologists from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aguilar-ecology.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;aguilar ecology lab&lt;/a&gt; who have a profound knowledge of the growth patterns of different fungal species (see Fig.1).
In a first &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/ismecommun/article/2/1/2/7460968&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;network analysis of our collaborators&lt;/a&gt;, they identified that some network traits vary most in between species, as for example the meshedness (how different the network is from a fully-connected one without crossing edges).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/2022Aguilar_network_paper_fig3adapted.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;800&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Fig.1 - Different species of hyphal growing fungi and the reconstruction of the network they are forming.
  Figure is adapted from &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/ismecommun/article/2/1/2/7460968&#34;&gt;Aguilar-Trigueros et al. (2022)&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We address the problem from a modeling perspective, that means we build an agent-based model, which is motivated from real fungi.
In our model each agent represents the tip of a hyphen and the tip as well as the whole hyphen release an enzyme.
This enzyme diffuses though the environment and other tips/agents can sense the local concentration and gradient.
This is all the information the tip has about its environment, i.e. only local information is allowed.
New Tips/Agents are created either by an apical branching event, at which one tip splits in two, or by a lateral branching event, where from the lower half of a tip compartment multiple branches grow perpendicular to the local growth direction.
By varying some fundamental parameters of the model as the diffusion coefficient, the enzyme release rate or the number of lateral branches, different shapes can emerge as shown if Fig. 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;./figures/3_mycel_compilation.png&#34; alt=&#34;drawing&#34; width=&#34;1200&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Fig.2 -
  Depending on the parameters, the mycelium grows densely (A) or less densely (B, C) if for example the enzyme release rate is increased (B)  or the septation rule is adapted (C). The enzyme in the environment (orange and red background color) inhibits the growth of the mycelium, thus the mycelium is more responsive to its own form (compare A with B). In (A, B) the septation and lateral branching form always two septa and branches at each septation event. In (C) 6 septa and branches are formed during a septation event. While the quadrants 2-4 show the concentration on a variable linear scale (bottom color bar), the 1st quadrant uses a fixed logarithmic scale (top color bar) to enable a fair comparison between simulations.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goals are now to reproduce key structural properties of real fungal species with a model as simple as possible, study the statistical properties of the different phases of the model and what task the fungi can perform beast at every phase.
This is exciting, especially because we are able to switch between theory, modelling and experiments.
The big picture is of course the role of the fungi in the ecosystems in connection with their growth strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complexity Explorables</title>
      <link>https://synosys.github.io/project/complexity_explorables/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://synosys.github.io/project/complexity_explorables/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
